<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Resistance Exercise Sessions Comprising Multijoint vs. Single-Joint Exercises Result in Similar Metabolic and Hormonal Responses, But Distinct Levels of Muscle Damage in Trained Men</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Paulo</forename><forename type="middle">Henrique</forename><surname>Barbosa</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Human Performance Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Methodist University of Piracicaba</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Piracicaba</settlement>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Julio</forename><forename type="middle">Benvenutti</forename><surname>Bueno De Camargo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Human Performance Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Methodist University of Piracicaba</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Piracicaba</settlement>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Neuromuscular Adaptations to Resistance Training (MUSCULAB)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Federal University of Sa˜o Carlos</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jonas</forename><surname>De Oliveira</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Centro Universit ário de Itajub á</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Itajub á</addrLine>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Carolina</forename><surname>Gabriela</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Reis</forename><surname>Barbosa</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Human Performance Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Methodist University of Piracicaba</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Piracicaba</settlement>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexsandro</forename><surname>Santos Da Silva</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Postgraduate Program in Movement Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Sa˜o Paulo State University (UNESP)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sa˜o Paulo</addrLine>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Julio</forename><surname>Wilson Dos-Santos</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Physical Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sa˜o Paulo State University (UNESP)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bauru</settlement>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Roz</forename><surname>Ângela Verlengia</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Human Performance Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Methodist University of Piracicaba</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Piracicaba</settlement>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Úlia Barreira</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Campinas</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Campinas Barbosa</settlement>
									<region>PH</region>
									<country key="BR">Brazil</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tiago</forename><surname>Volpi Braz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Human Performance Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Methodist University of Piracicaba</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Piracicaba</settlement>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Charles</forename><forename type="middle">Ricardo</forename><surname>Lopes</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Human Performance Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Methodist University of Piracicaba</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Piracicaba</settlement>
									<country>Brazil;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution">Bueno de Camargo</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>JB</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Jonas de Oliveira</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">J, Reis Barbosa</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>CG</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">Dos-Santos, JW</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Santos da Silva</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Verlengia, R</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Resistance Exercise Sessions Comprising Multijoint vs. Single-Joint Exercises Result in Similar Metabolic and Hormonal Responses, But Distinct Levels of Muscle Damage in Trained Men</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">15EF319390C847ED13C85C60E05532A3</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2026-03-22T22:18+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">b64991a</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>strength training</term>
					<term>growth hormone</term>
					<term>blood lactate</term>
					<term>energy expenditure</term>
					<term>creatine kinase</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Barreira, J, Braz, TV, and Lopes, CR. Resistance exercise sessions comprising multijoint vs. single-joint exercises result in similar metabolic and hormonal responses, but distinct levels of muscle damage in trained men. J Strength Cond Res 38(5): 842-847, 2024-Resistance-type exercise (RE) elicits distinct acute metabolic and hormonal responses, which can be modulated by the manipulation of training variables. The purpose of this study was to compare the metabolic (blood lactate and estimated lactic anaerobic system energy expenditure) and hormonal (growth hormone [GH]) responses to RE sessions composed exclusively of multijoint (MULTI) or single-joint (SINGLE) exercises. Assessments of creatine kinase (CK) levels were also performed. In a crossover design, 10 recreationally resistance-trained men (age: 26.9 6 3.0 years, total body mass: 83.2 6 13.8 kg; height: 176 6 7.0 cm; training experience: 5.5 6 2.4 years) were randomly submitted to both protocols. Blood collections were made pre, 3 minutes after, and 36 hours after each experimental session. No significant difference between MULTI vs. SINGLE was observed for the rises in blood lactate (p 5 0.057) and GH (p 5 0.285) levels. For CK, a significant difference between the protocols was noted, in which MULTI resulted in significant rises after 3 minutes (p 5 0.017) and 36 hours (p 5 0.043) compared with SINGLE. In conclusion, the findings of this study suggest that resistance-trained individuals display similar metabolic and hormonal responses when performing MULTI and SINGLE exercise protocols. Also, RE sessions comprising MULTI exercises induce a higher magnitude of muscle damage, which may require a longer recovery period compared with SINGLE.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Resistance-type exercise (RE) induces several acute metabolic and hormonal responses, which may present an important role in the subsequent skeletal tissue remodeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>. Different RE programs regarding intensity <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24)</ref>, volume <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>, and muscle actions <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> have been shown to result in distinct acute hormonal and metabolic responses. According to the practitioner's goal or demand, the type of exercise performed is another training variable that is usually manipulated by strength and conditioning coaches. Generally, RE can be labeled according to the number of joints involved in a specific movement as multijoint (MULTI) or single joint (SINGLE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>.</p><p>Although the type of exercise performed may eventually affect the acute responses to a given training session, this topic is still underinvestigated, especially in resistance-trained individuals. For blood lactate levels, recent data from our research group reported that trained men experienced significantly higher increases when performing a MULTI exercise (barbell bench press) compared with a SINGLE exercise (dumbbell fly) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>, which may be mainly explained by the higher volume load (VL) observed during the first.</p><p>It has been extensively reported that distinct RE protocols may influence the magnitude of acute hormonal responses (e.g., growth hormone <ref type="bibr">[GH]</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28)</ref>. Although RE protocols with higher total work and shorter rest intervals have been shown to induce the larger rises in GH, eventual influences of the type of exercise performed remains to be properly investigated.</p><p>In addition to metabolic disturbances, RE can also result in localized damage to the muscle tissue, which is usually accompanied by the release of enzymes such as creatine kinase (CK) into the blood, reductions in neuromuscular performance-related parameters, and also acute morphological responses (e.g., muscle swelling, limb circumference) <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>. The effects of different types of RE (MULTI vs. SINGLE) on indirect markers of muscle damage are not completely elucidated, with conflicting results being reported. Soares et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>, for example, observed that performing an exercise session exclusively composed of a SINGLE exercise (biceps curl) elicited higher delayed-onset muscle soreness (DOMS) and isometric strength reductions compared with MULTI (lat pull-down). Conversely, in a recent study from our research group <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, performing the back squat exercise (MULTI) resulted in a higher-magnitude elevation in indirect markers of muscle damage (limb circumference, muscle swelling, DOMS) compared with the knee extension exercise (SINGLE). These distinct results may be mainly explained by the fact that only protocols for the upper and lower limbs were adopted for Gentil et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> and De Camargo et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, respectively. In this sense, it is not completely clear whether the responses of the indirect markers of muscle damage assessed in each of these studies were resulted by the muscle groups stimulated within the session (upper-limb vs. lower-limb muscles) or the type of exercise (MULTI vs. SIN-GLE) itself. Therefore, experimental protocols, including both upper-limb and lower-limb exercises, within the same training session may help to provide further insight into this topic.</p><p>It is interesting to note that based on these investigations, although both metabolic and indirect markers of muscle damage outcomes may somewhat differ between MULTI and SINGLE exercises, they were limited to assessing these changes in exercise bouts that involved only 1 exercise, which impairs possible inferences toward training sessions performed by trained individuals in their usual training routines. Therefore, this study aimed to assess the acute metabolic (blood lactate, GH levels, and estimated anaerobic energy cost) and indirect muscle damage (CK levels) responses to performing MULTI vs. SINGLE exercise sessions. It was initially hypothesized that because of the higher amount of muscle mass involved and the magnitude of VL, the MULTI protocol would induce higher responses in all the dependent variables assessed compared with the SINGLE.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental Approach to the Problem</head><p>This study followed a randomized crossover design. Subjects visited the laboratory on 5 separate occasions (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>). The first visit consisted of collecting the Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire (PAR-Q), anthropometric data, 1-repetition maximum (1RM) test ( bench press and back squat exercises) followed by an 8 RM test (interspaced by 30 minutes) for all the exercises adopted during the experimental protocols. In the second visit (after 72 hours), MULTI or SINGLE exercise protocols were randomly performed, and 1 week later, each subject was submitted to the opposite protocol. Blood collections were made before, 3 minutes after, and 36 hours after each exercise session. The MULTI protocol consisted of the bench press, lat pull-down, and back squat exercises, and the SINGLE protocol consisted of the dumbbell fly, straight arm cable pull-down, and leg extension exercises. A 1-minute and 3-minute passive rest interval was afforded between sets and exercises, respectively. All subjects were instructed to keep their usual nutrition habits and to refrain from any exercise for 1 week before performing the experimental protocols.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subjects</head><p>Ten recreationally resistance-trained men (age: 26.9 6 3.0 years [range 19-34 years]; total body mass: 83.2 6 13.8 kg; height: 176 6 7.0 cm; training experience: 5.5 6 2.4 years [range 2-5 years]; training frequency: 5.3 6 0.7 sessions per week; relative back squat 1RM: 1.4 6 0.3) participated in the study. All subjects performed RE for a minimum of 3 days per week for at least 1 year and the exercises adopted in the experimental sessions (minimum frequency of once a week). In addition, subjects did not present any existing musculoskeletal disorders and negatively answered all questions on the PAR-Q. Subjects also displayed a minimum relative 1RM value for the squat and bench press exercises of at least 1.25 and 1.0 3 total body mass, respectively. This study was approved by the Methodist Piracicaba University's research ethics committee (protocol 13/19); all subjects read and signed an informed consent document.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Procedures</head><p>Experimental Acute Protocols. In random order (block randomization by a researcher not involved in the data collection process), subjects were submitted to both MULTI and SINGLE exercise protocols. During both sessions, they were instructed to perform a maximal number of repetitions until the point of concentric muscular failure with a load corresponding to 8 RM for 5 sets. Subjects reported a rating of perceived exertion (RPE) based on the repetitions in reserve (RIR) scale of 9.5-10 for all sets and exercises across both experimental sessions <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>. At baseline (1 week before the experimental sessions), an 8RM test for all the exercises adopted was performed within 3 attempts, with a rest interval of 5 minutes between the attempts and a 10-minute recovery period between exercises. The testing protocol followed previous recommendations by the National Strength and Conditioning Association (NSCA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>. The heaviest load achieved on 3 attempts was used to set the initial training load. Before the first set of each experimental condition, the subjects performed a specific warm-up, consisting of 8 repetitions at 50% of the 8RM. The loads were continually adjusted to keep the exercises in 8RM. A standard cadence of 4 seconds per repetition was adopted using a metronome (Metronome Beats, Stonekick, London, United Kingdom). A passive rest period of 60 second was adopted between the sets. Both protocols were accompanied by the same researchers. All volunteers received verbal encouragement during the exercises.</p><p>Maximal Dynamic Strength (1RM). Maximum dynamic strength was assessed through 1RM testing using the back squat (1RM SQUAT ) and bench press (1RM BENCH PRESS ) exercises. This test was performed to characterize the relative maximum dynamic strength of the sample, ensuring that all subjects displayed a minimum 1RM SQUAT and 1RM BENCH of 1.25 and 1.0 3 body mass, respectively (2). The testing protocol followed previous recommendations by the NSCA <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>. During the first set, subjects performed 5 repetitions at 50% of the estimated 1RM followed by 1 set of 3 repetitions at a load corresponding to 60-80% of the estimated 1RM with a 1-minute rest interval between the sets. After the warm-up sets, subjects had 3 attempts to find their 1RM load with 3-minute intervals between the trials. The 1RM was deemed as the maximum weight that could be lifted no more than once with the proper technique. All testing sessions were supervised by the same researchers.</p><p>Blood Lactate. Blood lactate concentration was assessed to estimate the anaerobic energy expenditure of each training session (post 3 minutes). Blood samples (25 ml) were collected from the fingertips into heparinized capillary tubes and transferred to microtubes containing 50 ml of 1% sodium fluoride. The lactate concentration was analyzed through an electroenzymatic method with a lactate analyzer (YSI 2300 Stat Analyzer, Yellow Springs Instruments, 2 Yellow Springs, OH). The values are expressed in millimoles 3 liter 21 (mmol•L 21 ).</p><p>Growth Hormone and Creatine Kinase Levels. Blood samples (;5 ml) were obtained by a standard venipuncture in 2 vacutainer tubes (Becton Dickinson, Juiz de Fora, Brazil), one containing heparin for plasma separation and the other for serum separation. After allowing to clot at room temperature for 30 minutes, both tubes were centrifuged at 2,000 rpm for 20 minutes at 4°C, and the plasma and serum samples were stored at 270°C for later analyses. Serum GH was assessed by radioimmunoassay and values are expressed in nanograms 3 liter 21 (ng•L 21 ). Serum CK activity was measured using an automated equipment Konelab 60i (Wiener Lab, Rosario, Argentina) at 37°C using a test kit (Wiener Lab), and values are expressed as international units 3 liter 21 (IU•L 21 ).</p><p>Estimated Anaerobic Energy Expenditure. According to the methodology previously described by Bertuzzi et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>, the GEDAE-LaB software (<ref type="url" target="http://www.gedaelab.org/">http://www.gedaelab.org/</ref>) was adopted to estimate the anaerobic lactic energy system contribution, in which the lactate accumulation (postexercise lactate minus resting lactate) was multiplied by the oxygen equivalent (3 ml•O 2 •kg 2 1 ) (8) and by the subject's body mass. The data are expressed in kilocalories (Kcal).</p><p>Volume Load. The VL (sets 3 repetitions 3 load [kg]) was calculated from training logs filled out by research assistants for each one of the experimental sessions (MULTI and SINGLE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>. The values are expressed in kilograms (kg).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p>The normality and homogeneity of the variances were verified using the Shapiro-Wilk and Levene's tests, respectively. Before analysis, all data were log transformed for analysis to reduce bias arising from non-uniformity error (heteroscedasticity). The mean, SD, and 95% confidence intervals (CI) were used after data normality was assumed. A 2 3 2 repeated-measures analysis of variance (ANOVA; interaction conditions [MULTI and SINGLE] 3 time [pre vs. post]) was used to compare the blood lactate and GH analysis. A 2 3 3 repeated-measures ANOVA (interaction conditions [MULTI and SINGLE] 3 time [pre, post, and post 36 hours]) was used to compare CK values. Post hoc comparisons were performed with the Bonferroni's correction. Assumptions of sphericity were evaluated using Mauchly's test. Where sphericity was violated (p , 0.05), the Greenhouse-Geisser correction factor was applied. In addition, an unpaired t test was used to compare VL, absolute differences in blood lactate, GH, and CK values and also anaerobic energy contribution between the protocols. The effect size (ES) in ANOVA was evaluated using a partial eta-squared (ɳ 2 p ) value of ,0.06 (small), 0.06-0.14 (medium), and .0.14 (large) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>. The ES in absolute difference (pre vs. post) was based on Cohen's d units by means (d value) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>. The ES result was qualitatively interpreted using the following thresholds: ,0.2, trivial; 0.2-0.6, small; 0.6-1.2, moderate; 1.2-2.0, large; 2.0-4.0, very large; and .4.0, extremely large. All analyses were conducted in SPSS-22.0 software (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY). The adopted significance was p , 0.05.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>For blood lactate, a significant main effect of time (F 1,36 5 156.7; ɳ 2 p 5 0.81), but not group 3 time interaction (F 1,36 5 3.939; ɳ 2 p 5 0.09), was observed (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). The ES of the absolute difference (pre-post) was extremely large for SINGLE (d 5 4.79) and very large for MULTI (d 5 3.75). The ES between the protocols was moderate (d 5 0.91).</p><p>For GH, a significant main effect of time (F 1,36 5 30.23; ɳ 2 p 5 0.46), but not group 3 time interaction (F 1,36 5 10.82; ɳ 2 p 5 0.03), was observed (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). The ES of the absolute difference (pre-post) was large for both SINGLE (d 5 1.55) and MULTI (d 5 1.96). The ES between the protocols was small (d 5 0.49).</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> displays CK values pre, post 3 minutes, and post 36 hours for each experimental protocol. A significant main effect of time for MULTI (F 2,48 5 13.18; ɳ 2 p 5 0.35), but not group 3 time interaction (F 2,48 5 23.57; ɳ 2 p 5 0.05), was observed. The ES of the absolute difference (pre to 3 minutes) was small for SINGLE (d 5 0.45) and large for MULTI; (d 5 1.49), and the ES of the absolute difference (pre to 36 hours) was moderate for SINGLE (d 5 0.86) and large for MULTI (d 5 1.80). The ES between the protocols was large for pre to 3 minutes (d 5 1.16) and moderate for pre to 36 hours (d 5 0.97).</p><p>No significant difference was observed between the protocols for the estimated anaerobic energy cost (p 5 0.075; mean difference [MD] 5 3.10; 95% CI 5 20.34 to 6.54 kcal; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>).  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>The aim of this study was to compare the acute metabolic and hormonal responses between MULTI vs. SINGLE training sessions, which comprised exercises for both upper and lower limbs. In addition, the levels of an indirect marker of muscle damage (CK) were also assessed. Our initial hypothesis was partially confirmed because both blood lactate and GH rises did not differ between the exercise protocols, but the MULTI session did result in significant CK increases post 36 hours.</p><p>Resistance exercise is an effective physiological stimulus for increasing both GH and ( <ref type="formula">29</ref>) and blood lactate levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>. Although both exercise bouts induced significant rises in plasma GH and lactate levels, no difference was noted between the protocols. Our initial hypothesis was that because of the larger amount of muscle mass involved and total work performed, MULTI would induce a higher rise in postexercise serum GH and lactate. The acute responses of both variables are strongly influenced by RE protocols with higher volumes <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21)</ref>. Hansen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>, for example, reported that the higher VL observed when performing MULTI (leg press) in addition to a SINGLE exercise (biceps curl) induced higher rises in GH compared with an exclusively SINGLE session. This effect on acute GH responses elicited by exercise sessions with higher VL was also reported by other investigations <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15)</ref>. Notwithstanding, similar to another investigation <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>, the larger VL observed by this study for the MULTI compared with the SINGLE protocol (7,302 6 1,284 kg vs. 5,590 6 1,054 kg, respectively) was not sufficient to induce significantly larger rises in serum GH and lactate levels. Therefore, although somewhat speculative, there may exist a threshold of total work performed that is required to result in significant differences in both hormonal and metabolic responses throughout the early recovery period, especially for previously trained subjects. Additional studies are warranted to provide further insight on to which extent the total work performed is related to these responses following distinct RE protocols. Moreover, because this is the first controlled study that evaluated the effect of MULTI vs. SINGLE exercise protocols on GH and lactate responses, we cannot directly compare our findings with other studies.</p><p>Although the exact role of exercise-induced metabolites and hormonal rises in mediating muscular responses to RE programs is far from being elucidated, GH release seems to be somehow associated with blood lactate levels. This relationship arises from studies that reported a blunted exercise-induced GH response in healthy subjects following the administration of alkaline compounds (sodium bicarbonate) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> and also in patients with McArdle's disease, which present an impaired capacity for elevating blood lactate levels within exercise testing of progressive load <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. Therefore, the lacking of difference in GH response between MULTI and SINGLE protocols in this study may also be justified by the similar increases in blood lactate levels induced by both experimental conditions.</p><p>In addition to blood lactate levels, this study also assessed anaerobic lactic pathway-estimated energy expenditure as an indirect measure of glycolytic activity, with no significant difference emerging between the experimental protocols. Eventual comparisons with other studies cannot be properly done because this is the first investigation that compared distinct RE sessions regarding the type of exercises performed (MULTI vs. SINGLE) and their acute effects on the lactic metabolism contribution. Our initial hypothesis was that because of a strong and positive association between total work performed and anaerobic energy cost within a RE session <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>, the larger VL performed during MULTI would result in an increased energetic contribution of the anaerobic system compared with the SINGLE session. Brunelli et al. (4), for example, reported a higher contribution of the anaerobic energetic pathway following an RE  In addition, the same exercise (leg extension) performed with different relative intensity and also distinct VL values was performed. Therefore, based on our findings, although a trend was observed favoring the MULTI protocol (p 5 0.075), it can be suggested that the contribution of the anaerobic lactic system during an RE session is not dependent on the exercise performed as long as a high-intensity protocol is performed to the point of momentary concentric muscular failure. The authors of this study strongly encourage that additional investigations be performed to further elucidate our findings and also help strength and conditioning coaches to optimally manipulate the type of exercise performed within RE sessions according to specific goals or demands of each practitioner.</p><p>For CK levels, significant increases from pre to post 36 hours were noted only for the MULTI protocol. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> shows a greater increase in CK levels for 2 individuals in the MULTI protocol, reinforcing the individual variability of this marker after the resistance training. After performing the statistical analysis without these 2 cases, we found the same results corroborating that the findings are not only dependent on these 2 individuals but rather represent the group. Although not completely understood, this may be mainly attributed to the fact that the accumulated volume of work seems to be the primary determinant of exerciseinduced CK rises in trained subjects <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>. This result confirms previous findings from our laboratory <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, in which performing exclusively the back squat exercise elicited higher post-36 hour rises in indirect markers of muscle damage (leg circumference, muscle swelling, muscle soreness) compared with performing the knee extension exercise. Different from this study, Soares et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> reported that a SINGLE protocol resulted in highermagnitude rises in muscle damage markers compared with a MULTI one. Although the subjects presented similar training backgrounds, some methodological differences must be acknowledged to compare the distinct results between Soares et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> and the current study. First, neuromuscular performance (elbow flexor peak torque) and muscle soreness-related outcomes were assessed as indirect markers of muscle damage by Soares et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>. In this sense, it is important to highlight that postexercise rises in CK levels are not necessarily associated with other markers of muscle damage, such as muscle strength and soreness <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>. Second, 36 hours postexercise assessments were not performed by Soares et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>. Moreover, although this investigation assessed the responses to an exercise session composed of 3 exercises (lower and upper limbs), only 1 exercise was performed in each protocol by Soares et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> (unilateral seated row and biceps curl for MULTI and SINGLE, respectively). Therefore, from an entire training session standpoint, further investigations must be addressed to better understand the responses of indirect markers of muscle damage to MULTI vs. SINGLE exercise protocols.  The main limitation of this study is that no further analysis was performed during the later phases of the recovery period (e.g., 48, 72, 96 hours postexercise sessions). Therefore, it is unclear whether similar metabolic and muscle damage patterns would be observed throughout additional assessments. It is also important to highlight that the results reported in this study refer only to recreationally trained men. In this sense, future studies with other populations (e.g., untrained, women, older subjects) must be encouraged to provide a better understanding of this topic. Finally, inferences regarding muscle damage must be done with caution because only CK levels were assessed. The validity of the analysis of CK for reflecting exercise-induced skeletal muscle damage is still controversial within the literature because factors such as training level and gender can influence CK levels to a greater extent than differences in exercise volume completed <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>. Therefore, future studies investigating other indirect markers of muscle tissue damage such as neuromuscular performance, morphological parameters (e.g., muscle swelling, limb circumference), and muscle soreness-related parameters must be conducted to provide further insight into this topic.</p><p>In conclusion, the results of this study suggest that the magnitude of muscle tissue damage seems to be influenced by the type of exercise performed within an exercise bout by recreationally resistancetrained individuals. In addition, MULTI and SINGLE protocols result in similar acute metabolic and hormonal responses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Practical Applications</head><p>The information provided by the current investigation may be of great relevance for strength and conditioning coaches when prescribing and implementing strength training programs. From a practical standpoint, both protocols are feasible to be implemented within high-intensity RE programs that aim to elevate both metabolic and hormonal stress. Also, based on our findings, it can be suggested that RE sessions comprising MULTI exercises induce a higher magnitude of skeletal muscle tissue damage, which may require a longer recovery period compared with SINGLE. Future studies must be conducted to investigate whether this increased stress observed in the MULTI protocol would result in augmented chronic adaptations. Finally, the results of this study also suggest that exercise sessions comprising exclusively SINGLE exercises may be adopted in specific contexts that require a reduced stressful stimulus, such as sessions performed within precompetition phases.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>displays the comparison of the absolute difference (post 2 pre) between the protocols for the dependent variables assessed. No significant difference between MULTI vs. SINGLE was observed for the rises in blood lactate (p 5 0.057; MD 5 2.59, 95% CI 5 20.09 to 5.27 mmol•L 21 ) and GH levels (p 5 0.285, MD 5 0.93, 95% CI 5 20.82 to 2.73 ng•L 21 ). For CK, a significant difference between the protocols was noted, in which MULTI resulted in significantly higher rises after 3 minutes (p 5 0.017; MD 5 94.4, 95% CI 5 18.3-170.5 IU•L 21 ) and 36 hours (p 5 0.043; MD 5 146.7, 95% CI 5 5.18-288.2 IU•L 21 ) compared with SINGLE.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Experimental design of the study. BS 5 back squat; BP 5 bench press; h 5 hours; wk 5 week.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,107.04,60.83,394.25,97.91" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Creatine kinase (CK) pre, 3 minutes after, and 36 hours after each training session for SINGLE and MULTI interventions. SINGLE 5 single-joint protocol; MULTI 5 multijoint protocol; *Significantly different compared with the premoment (p , 0.001).</figDesc><graphic coords="4,142.70,580.65,313.88,124.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Estimated anaerobic lactic energy system contribution; SINGLE 5 single-joint protocol; MULTI 5 multijoint protocol.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,79.94,60.83,190.03,96.38" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Absolute different (pre-post) for blood lactate (A), growth hormone (B), pre to 3 minutes (C), and pre to 36 hours (D) for creatine kinase. SINGLE 5 single-joint protocol; MULTI 5 multijoint protocol; GH 5 growth hormone; CK 5 creatine kinase. *Significantly different from SINGLE.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,123.25,445.32,361.87,259.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Pre and post values for blood lactate and growth hormone (mean 6 SD).* SINGLE 5 single-joint protocol; MULTI 5 multijoint protocol; GH 5 growth hormone; MD (95% CI) 5 mean difference (95% confidence interval); p 5 p value.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Time</cell><cell>Time 3 group</cell></row><row><cell>Variables</cell><cell>Pre</cell><cell>Post</cell><cell>MD [95% CI]</cell><cell>p</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell>Lactate (mmol•L 21 )</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SINGLE</cell><cell>1.19 6 0.17</cell><cell>8.11 6 2.03</cell><cell>6.92 [4.4-9.3]</cell><cell>0.001</cell><cell>0.054</cell></row><row><cell>MULTI</cell><cell>1.36 6 0.40</cell><cell>10.87 6 3.56</cell><cell>9.51 [7.0-11.9]</cell><cell>0.001</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>GH (ng•L 21 )</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SINGLE</cell><cell>0.04 6 0.04</cell><cell>1.97 6 1.75</cell><cell>1.93 [0.2-3.6]</cell><cell>0.016</cell><cell>0.305</cell></row><row><cell>MULTI</cell><cell>0.04 6 0.03</cell><cell>2.90 6 2.06</cell><cell>2.86 [1.1-4.5]</cell><cell>0.001</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>*</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Copyright © 2023 National Strength and Conditioning Association. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			
			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>The authors are grateful to all the volunteers that took part in the study. The authors declare they have no conflicts of interest. The results of this study do not constitute endorsement by the authors or the National Strength and Conditioning Association.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GEDAE-LaB: A free software to calculate the energy system contributions during exercise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bertuzzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Melegati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bueno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">145733</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bertuzzi R, Melegati J, Bueno S, et al. GEDAE-LaB: A free software to calculate the energy system contributions during exercise. PLoS One 11: e0145733, 2016.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of resistance training frequency on neuromuscular performance and muscle morphology after 8 weeks in trained men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brigatto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Braz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tcc</forename><surname>Zanini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Strength Cond Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2104" to="2116" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Brigatto FA, Braz TV, Zanini TCC, et al. Effect of resistance training frequency on neuromuscular performance and muscle morphology after 8 weeks in trained men. J Strength Cond Res 33: 2104-2116, 2019.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison between the total load raised and blood lactate in response to strength exercise sessions performed with multiarticular and monoarticular exercise in trained men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brigatto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Braz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Da Conceição</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev Bras Prescrição e Fisiol do Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1354" to="1360" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Brigatto FA, Braz TV, da Conceição RM, et al. Comparison between the total load raised and blood lactate in response to strength exercise sessions performed with multiarticular and monoarticular exercise in trained men. Rev Bras Prescrição e Fisiol do Exerc 13: 1354-1360, 2019.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acute low-compared to highload resistance training to failure results in greater energy expenditure during exercise in healthy young men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Brunelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ear</forename><surname>Finardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ilp</forename><surname>Bonfante</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">224801</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Brunelli DT, Finardi EAR, Bonfante ILP, et al. Acute low-compared to high- load resistance training to failure results in greater energy expenditure during exercise in healthy young men. PLoS One 14: e0224801, 2019.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Possible stimuli for strength and power adaptation: Acute metabolic responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Crewther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cronin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Keogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sports Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Crewther B, Cronin J, Keogh J. Possible stimuli for strength and power adaptation: Acute metabolic responses. Sports Med 36: 65-78, 2006.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The widespread misuse of effect sizes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dankel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mouser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mattocks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Sci Med Sport</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="446" to="450" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dankel SJ, Mouser JG, Mattocks KT, et al. The widespread misuse of effect sizes. J Sci Med Sport 20: 446-450, 2017.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dissociated time course of indirect markers of muscle damage recovery between single-joint and multi-joint exercises in resistance-trained men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jbb</forename><surname>De Camargo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Braz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Batista</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Strength Cond Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2089" to="2093" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">de Camargo JBB, Braz TV, Batista DR, et al. Dissociated time course of indirect markers of muscle damage recovery between single-joint and multi-joint exercises in resistance-trained men. J Strength Cond Res 36: 2089-2093, 2022.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The energetics of anaerobic muscle metabolism: A reappraisal of older and recent concepts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Prampero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ferretti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Respir Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Di Prampero PE, Ferretti G. The energetics of anaerobic muscle metabo- lism: A reappraisal of older and recent concepts. Respir Physiol 118: 103-115, 1999.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hormonal responses from concentric and eccentric muscle contractions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Durand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Castracane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hollander</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Sci Sports Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="937" to="943" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Durand RJ, Castracane VD, Hollander DB, et al. Hormonal responses from concentric and eccentric muscle contractions. Med Sci Sports Exerc 35: 937-943, 2003.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of blood pH and blood lactate on growth hormone, prolactin, and gonadotropin release after acute exercise in male volunteers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Elias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Naqvi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pandian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Soc Exp Biol Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">214</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Elias AN, Wilson AF, Naqvi S, Pandian MR. Effects of blood pH and blood lactate on growth hormone, prolactin, and gonadotropin release after acute exercise in male volunteers. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 214: 156-160, 1997.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of workload quantification methods in relation to physiological responses to resistance exercise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Genner</forename><surname>Kyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Strength Cond Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2621" to="2627" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Genner Kyle M, Weston M. A comparison of workload quantification methods in relation to physiological responses to resistance exercise. J Strength Cond Res 28: 2621-2627, 2014.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single vs. multi-joint resistance exercises: Effects on muscle strength and hypertrophy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gentil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Soares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bottaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Asian J Sports Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gentil P, Soares S, Bottaro M. Single vs. multi-joint resistance exercises: Effects on muscle strength and hypertrophy. Asian J Sports Med 6: 1-5, 2015.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of lactate in the exercise-induced human growth hormone response: Evidence from McArdle disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Godfrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Whyte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Buckley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Quinlivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Sports Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="525" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Godfrey RJ, Whyte GP, Buckley J, Quinlivan R. The role of lactate in the exercise-induced human growth hormone response: Evidence from McArdle disease. Br J Sports Med 43: 521-525, 2009.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hormonal responses of multiset versus single-set heavy-resistance exercise protocols</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gotshalk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Loebel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Nindl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Can J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="244" to="255" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gotshalk LA, Loebel CC, Nindl BC, et al. Hormonal responses of multiset versus single-set heavy-resistance exercise protocols. Can J Appl Physiol 22: 244-255, 1997.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acute hormonal responses to two different fatiguing heavy-resistance protocols in male athletes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>H Äkkinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pakarinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="882" to="887" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">H äkkinen K, Pakarinen A. Acute hormonal responses to two different fatiguing heavy-resistance protocols in male athletes. J Appl Physiol 74: 882-887, 1993.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of short-term strength training on human skeletal muscle: The importance of physiologically elevated hormone levels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kvorning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kjaer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sjøgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scand J Med Sci Sports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="347" to="354" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hansen S, Kvorning T, Kjaer M, Sjøgaard G. The effect of short-term strength training on human skeletal muscle: The importance of physiologically elevated hormone levels. Scand J Med Sci Sports 11: 347-354, 2001.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of the repetitions in reserve-based rating of perceived exertion scale for resistance training</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Helms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cronin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Storey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Zourdos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strength Cond J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Helms ER, Cronin J, Storey A, Zourdos MC. Application of the repeti- tions in reserve-based rating of perceived exertion scale for resistance training. Strength Cond J 38: 42-49, 2016.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The creatine kinase response to resistance exercise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Machado</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Musculoskelet Neuronal Interact</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="68" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Koch AJ, Pereira R, Machado M. The creatine kinase response to re- sistance exercise. J Musculoskelet Neuronal Interact 14: 68-77, 2014.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hormonal responses and adaptations to resistance exercise and training</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kraemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ratamess</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sports Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="361" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kraemer WJ, Ratamess NA. Hormonal responses and adaptations to re- sistance exercise and training. Sports Med 35: 339-361, 2005.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hormonal and growth factor responses to heavy resistance exercise protocols</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kraemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Marchitelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1442" to="1450" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kraemer WJ, Marchitelli L, Gordon SE, et al. Hormonal and growth factor responses to heavy resistance exercise protocols. J Appl Physiol 69: 1442-1450, 1990.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in hormonal concentrations after different heavy-resistance exercise protocols in women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kraemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fleck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dziados</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="594" to="604" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kraemer WJ, Fleck SJ, Dziados JE, et al. Changes in hormonal concen- trations after different heavy-resistance exercise protocols in women. J Appl Physiol 75: 594-604, 1993.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of varying rest intervals between sets of assistance exercises on creatine kinase and lactate dehydrogenase responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Machado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Willardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Strength Cond Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1339" to="1345" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Machado M, Koch AJ, Willardson JM, et al. Effect of varying rest inter- vals between sets of assistance exercises on creatine kinase and lactate dehydrogenase responses. J Strength Cond Res 25: 1339-1345, 2011.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hormonal responses to high-and moderateintensity strength exercise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Raastad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bjøro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hallén</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Raastad T, Bjøro T, Hallén J. Hormonal responses to high-and moderate- intensity strength exercise. Eur J Appl Physiol 82: 121-128, 2000.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acute effects of different intensities of weight lifting on serum testosterone</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schwab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Housh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kinder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Weir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Sci Sports Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1381" to="1385" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schwab R, Johnson GO, Housh TJ, Kinder JE, Weir JP. Acute effects of different intensities of weight lifting on serum testosterone. Med Sci Sports Exerc 25: 1381-1385, 1993.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of time-under-tension and weight lifting cadence on aerobic, anaerobic, and recovery energy expenditures: 3 submaximal sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl Physiol Nutr Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="252" to="256" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Scott CB. The effect of time-under-tension and weight lifting cadence on aerobic, anaerobic, and recovery energy expenditures: 3 submaximal sets. Appl Physiol Nutr Metab 37: 252-256, 2012.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Program Design for Resistance Training</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sheppard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Triplett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Essentials of Strength Training and Conditioning</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Champaign, IL</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Human Kinetics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="452" to="454" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th ed.</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sheppard JM, Triplett NT: Program Design for Resistance Training, in Es- sentials of Strength Training and Conditioning (4th ed.). Champaign, IL: Human Kinetics, 2016. pp. 452-454.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dissociated time course of muscle damage recovery between single-and multi-joint exercises in highly resistance-trained men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Soares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ferreira-Junior</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Strength Cond Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2594" to="2599" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Soares S, Ferreira-Junior JB, Pereira MC, et al. Dissociated time course of muscle damage recovery between single-and multi-joint exercises in highly resistance-trained men. J Strength Cond Res 29: 2594-2599, 2015.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Growth hormone responses during intermittent weight lifting exercise in men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Vanhelder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Radomski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Goode</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vanhelder WP, Radomski MW, Goode RC. Growth hormone responses during intermittent weight lifting exercise in men. Eur J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol 53: 31-34, 1984.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Elevations in ostensibly anabolic hormones with resistance exercise enhance neither training-induced muscle hypertrophy nor strength of the elbow flexors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dwd</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Burd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">West DWD, Burd NA, Tang JE, et al. Elevations in ostensibly anabolic hormones with resistance exercise enhance neither training-induced muscle hypertrophy nor strength of the elbow flexors. J Appl Physiol 108: 60-67, 2010.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
