<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Acute psycho-physiological responses to perceptually regulated hypoxic and normoxic interval walks in overweight-to-obese adults</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2020-11-30">30 November 2020</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Liam</forename><surname>Hobbins</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Sport and Exercise Science Research Centre (SESRC)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">London South Bank University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Girard</surname></persName>
							<email>olivier.girard@uwa.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Human Sciences (Exercise and Sport Science)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Western Australia</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nadia</forename><surname>Gaoua</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Sport and Exercise Science Research Centre (SESRC)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">London South Bank University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Steve</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Sport and Exercise Science Research Centre (SESRC)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">London South Bank University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Acute psycho-physiological responses to perceptually regulated hypoxic and normoxic interval walks in overweight-to-obese adults</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2020-11-30">30 November 2020</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5D8BD5603666E9B1C907D16C7D68A987</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jsams.2020.11.011</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 10 June 2020 Received in revised form 2 October 2020 Accepted 16 November 2020</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2026-03-22T22:17+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">b64991a</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Hypoxia Perceptually regulated exercise Interval training Obesity</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Objectives: We investigated psycho-physiological responses to perceptually regulated interval walks in hypoxia versus normoxia in obese individuals. Design: Within-participants repeated measures. Methods: Ten obese adults (BMI = 32 ± 3 kg/m -2 ) completed a 60-min interval session (15 × 2 min walking at a rating of perceived exertion of 14 on the 6-20 Borg scale with 2 min of rest) either in hypoxia (FiO 2 = 13.0%, HYP) or normoxia (NOR). A third trial replicating the HYP speed pattern was carried out in normoxia as a control (CON). Exercise responses were analysed comparing the average of 1st to 3rd exercise bouts to those of the 4th-6th, 7th-9th, 10th-12th and 13th-15th exercise bouts (block 1 versus 2, 3, 4 and 5). Results: Treadmill speed was slower during block 4 (6.14 ± 0.67 versus 6.24 ± 0.73 km/h -1 ) and block 5 (6.12 ± 0.64 versus 6.25 ± 0.75 km/h -1 ) in HYP compared to NOR or CON (p = 0.009). Compared to NOR and CON, heart rate was +6-10% higher (p = 0.001), whilst arterial oxygen saturation (-12-13%) was lower (p &lt; 0.001) in HYP. Perceived limb discomfort was lower in HYP and CON versus NOR (-21 ± 4% and -34 ± 6%; p = 0.004). Conclusions: In overweight-to-obese adults, perceptually regulated interval walks in hypoxia versus normoxia leads to progressively slower speeds along with lower limb discomfort and larger physiological stress than normoxia. Walking at the speed adopted in hypoxia produces similar psycho-physiological responses at the same absolute intensity in normoxia.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Obesity is typically caused by a positive energy balance, often accompanied by elevated blood pressure and metabolic defi-ciencies, which eventually leads to excess fat accumulation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Co-morbidities such as cardiovascular disease, hypertension and Type 2 Diabetes are therefore at greater risk of development in obese populations resulting in the likelihood of higher mortality rates. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Walking is an effective strategy to increase the energy expenditure of physical activity and exercise in unhealthy individuals, including adults with obesity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> Walking at a fixed-intensity (60% of maximal oxygen uptake [VO 2MAX ]) for 45-60 min, 1-5 times per week for at least six weeks, leads to a plethora of health improvements in obese individuals. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> A study of one hundred seventy-five sedentary, overweight men and women with mild to moderate dyslipidaemia over 8 months indicated a clear doseresponse relationship between increase in exercise amount and decreases in visceral, subcutaneous and total abdominal fat, without changes in caloric intake. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> Exercise-related sensations (i.e., perceived recovery, motivation, breathlessness, limb discomfort and pleasure), either measured during or following exercise, likely have a significant influence on adherence to training. This is especially true in obese individuals who are typically facing higher-than-normal exercise-induced physiological and perceptual responses. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> In obese individuals, Ekkekakis and Lind <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> showed that an acute bout of self-paced, continuous walking (20 min) increases post-exercise enjoyment above baseline, whereas imposing a 10% higher exercise intensity decreased enjoyment levels. Therefore, perceptually regulated walking that consists of matching a rating of perceived exertion [RPE] target, as opposed to a pre-determined fixed-intensity, may be a more effective approach to prescribing exercise in this population. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> Exercise with the addition of hypoxia provides a unique challenge to the cardiovascular system, due to immediate changes in convective oxygen delivery as a result of modifications from arterial oxygen content. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> This represents a promising exercise modality to increase the cardiovascular intensity of the session, without a corresponding elevation in the mechanical load imposed on the musculoskeletal system. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> In healthy individuals, acute muscle oxygenation responses didn't differ during constant-load exercise (75% maximal heart rate [HR MAX ] for 30 min) or high-intensity interval (15 × 1-min exercise with 1-min rest) cycling exercise performed in hypoxia (inspired fraction of oxygen or FiO 2 = 13.5%) at the same relative intensity (similar hear rate) compared to normoxia. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> However, fixed-intensity exercise does not permit the necessary adjustments to maintain a target exercise intensity that could potentially augment physiological stress levels in O 2 -deprived conditions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> Our previous work demonstrated that trained runners carrying out perceptually regulated interval runs (4 × 4 min running at a RPE of 16 on the 6-20 Borg scale with 3 min of rest) adjusted to a slower speed in hypoxia than normoxia, with similar levels of physiological stress (i.e., HR and vastus lateralis muscle oxygenation) levels. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> Nonetheless, studies including a perceptually regulated interval protocol have not been carried out in an obese population, yet the potential findings could be promising for acute psycho-physiological responses when in hypoxia compared to normoxia.</p><p>Our intention was to compare, in overweight-to-obese individuals, the acute effects of a 60-min perceptually regulated (RPE = 14) interval walking (2 min of exercise interspersed with 2 min of rest) session in hypoxia and normoxia on psycho-physiological responses. We hypothesised that walking speed becomes progressively slower in hypoxia compared to normoxia when perceptually regulated, which results in similar adjustments in physiological and perceptual responses. In order to ascertain that these aforementioned changes are due to hypoxic exposure per se, and not a side effect of hypoxia-related expected reduction in walking speed, it was necessary to replicate the exercise pattern that participants self-selected in hypoxia but carried out in normoxia. Only then any potential psycho-physiological difference between O 2 -deprived and near sea level conditions could accurately be attributed to the stress of acute hypoxia. Therefore, a second aim was to investigate whether walking at the perceptually regulated speed adopted in hypoxia produces similar psycho-physiological responses at the same absolute intensity in normoxia. When the speed selected by participants in hypoxia is subsequently replicated in normoxia, we anticipated that a lower physiological/metabolic stress would accompany similar adjustments in exercise-related sensations and cognitive function.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Methods</head><p>Ten overweight-to-obese (7 males, 3 females; age: 38.2 ± 11.9 years; stature: 171 ± 10 cm; body weight: 93.8 ± 10.1 kg; body mass index: 32.1 ± 2.8 kg/m -2 ) individuals participated in this study after meeting the eligibility criteria and providing written informed consent. Eligible volunteers were those who had a body mass index of 27-35 kg/m -2 , being normotensive (90-120 and 60-80 mmHg systolic and diastolic blood pressure, respectively), no known cardiovascular, metabolic or physiological illness/disease, sedentary (&lt;1 h of moderate-intensity exercise/week), and no exposure to altitude (≥2500 m) for &gt;48 h within six months. A sample size estimation was determined from a priori power analysis, using computer software G*Power 3.1, to detect differences (effect size = 0.91, power of 0.80, alpha of 0.05) on treadmill speeds with effects sizes calculated from previous research assessing the effects of perceptually-regulated (RPE = 16) normoxic and hypoxic (FiO 2 = 15%) interval runs on this variable. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> It was determined that 9 participants were required, with 10 allowing for a 10% attrition rate. This study received ethical approval from the School of Applied Science, London South Bank University (SAS1725) and was carried out in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki (2013).</p><p>Participants attended the laboratory on four separate occasions. The first session consisted of eligibility determination, familiarisation with the measures and treadmill walking, and identification of preferred walking speed. Within 72 h, participants returned to the laboratory for the first of three experimental trials, each separated by seven days to enable a washout period. Participants completed a 60-min interval session (15 × 2 min walking, 2 min resting) during each experimental trial. The first and second experimental trials included exposure to either hypoxia (HYP, FiO 2 = 13.0%/∼3750 m simulated altitude) or normoxia (NOR), with the order of intervention randomised, whilst the interval walking intensity was perceptually regulated (RPE = 14). The final experimental trial was the control (CON), where participants were exposed to normoxia and the intensity self-selected during HYP was imposed. The interval duration (work:rest ratio; 2:2 min) selected in the current study was based upon our previous findings. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> Each interval session was followed by a 60-min recovery period in normoxia.</p><p>At the preliminary visit to the laboratory, the preferred walking speed associated with an RPE of 14 (between 'somewhat hard' and 'hard') was determined for each participant in normoxia using a modified version of Martin et al., <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> as described previously. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> After a standardised 5-min warm up at 3.0 km/h -1 , participants completed four ramped treadmill walks with increasing and decreasing speeds. After every 15 s per ramp, participants rated their RPE of the current speed (controlled by the investigator and out of sight of the participant) in accordance with Borg's 6 ("no exertion at all") -20 ("maximal exertion") numeric scale. Ramp one started at 3 km/h -1 , increasing by 0.5 km/h -1 every 20 s until the speed was considered as RPE ≥ 16; ramp two started at +0.5 km/h -1 the previous end speed, decreasing by 0.5 km/h -1 until the speed was considered as RPE ≤ 10; ramp three started at the speed considered as an RPE of 12 in ramp two, increasing by 0.5 km/h -1 until the speed was considered as RPE ≥ 16; and ramp four started at +0.5 km/h -1 the previous end speed, decreasing by 0.5 km/h -1 until the speed was considered as RPE ≤ 10.</p><p>After a standardised 5-min warm up at 3.0 km/h -1 , a facemask connected to a portable hypoxic generator was attached to the participants (described further below). Participants completed 15 × 2-min walking intervals, each separated by 2 min of passive recovery (quiet standing). The first 30 s of each 2-min interval began at participants' preferred walking speed associated with an RPE of 14 during all sessions. During the HYP and NOR trials, participants were free to decide if and how treadmill speed needed to be altered every 30 s (i.e., self-paced and adjusted manually by the investigator) to ensure maintenance of RPE = 14, whilst walking. Participants hand-signalled in response to the current speed (finger up to increase, finger down to decrease, and circle using index finger and thumb to maintain); and signalled again to inform how much of an increase/decrease in speed is required [1, 2 or 3 fingers up (faster) or down (slower) for 0.2, 0.4 or 0.6 km/h -1 changes, respectively].</p><p>Signals were trialled during familiarisation. Participants were not required to make any adjustments during CON.</p><p>Participants wore a facemask connected to a hypoxic generator (Everest Training Summit II, Hypoxico Altitude Training Systems, USA). When breathing 'normal air' during normoxic conditions, the hypoxic generator was set at a simulated altitude of 100 m to increase the strength of blinding of the intervention. The study was designed as a single-blind fashion protocol in which participants, but not investigators, were blinded toward the environmental conditions. Total hypoxic exposure corresponded to exactly 60 min during HYP with the facemask remaining attached across all interval walking sessions.</p><p>Treadmill speed was manually recorded. A chest strap (H10, Polar, Finland) connected via Bluetooth to a watch (M400, Polar, Finland) permitted HR recording. Arterial oxygen saturation (SpO 2 ) was assessed via finger pulse oximetry (iHealth Air, iHealthLabs, USA). Both HR watch and oximeter receiver were attached on the handrails on the sides of the treadmill in a manner to not allow participants to view any data. These measures were assessed every 30 s during each 2-min interval.</p><p>Perceived recovery was assessed by answering 'how recovered do you feel currently?' via a numeric scale, ranging from 0 ('very poorly recovered') to 10 ('very well recovered'). <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> Recovery was assessed before interval one to determine perceptions following the warmup. Perceived motivation to exercise was assessed via a 20-cm visual analog scale. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> Participants were asked 'how motivated do you feel to exercise right now?' and answered by adjusting the level on the scale between 0 ('extremely low', white colored) and 20 ('extremely high', black colored). Perceived recovery and motivation to exercise were assessed 30 s before each interval.</p><p>Perceived breathlessness was assessed by answering 'how does your breathing feel currently?' via a numeric scale, ranging from 0 ('nothing at all') to 10 ('very, very severe'). <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> Using the same scale, perceived limb discomfort was assessed by answering 'how do your legs feel currently?'. A 20 cm visual analog scale (the same as motivation above) was used to assess 'how pleasant was that run?' ranging from 0 ("extremely unpleasant") and 20 ("extremely pleasant"). Ratings of perceived breathlessness, limb discomfort and pleasure were assessed immediately after each interval.</p><p>Perceived mood state, positive and negative affects (PANAS) and exercise self-efficacy were assessed at baseline and immediately (Post0), 30 (Post30) and 60 (Post60) min after the interval walking session. Participants were asked 'how are you feeling right now?' and instructed to verbally specify a number on an 11-point scale anchored 'very bad' (-5) up to 'very good' (+5) for perceived mood state. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> PANAS were assessed via a 20-item 5-point Likert scale. Participants were instructed to answer how they feel towards 20 emotions including 'interested', 'distressed' and 'excited', ranging from 'very slightly or not at all' (1) to 'extremely' (5). Items were totaled for positive and negative responses. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> Exercise self-efficacy was assessed via a six item 11-point Likert scale. Participants were instructed to answer how confident they feel in 'carrying out exercise 3 times per week at a moderate-intensity for 40+ minutes without quitting' for 1-6 months from 'not at all confident' (0) up to 'highly confident'. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> This Likert scale was in reference to exercise generally, and not the exercise employed in this study.</p><p>Treadmill speed, HR and SpO 2 values were averaged across each 2-min interval. Treadmill speed, HR, SpO 2 , and perceptual measures assessed during the interval walking sessions were condensed by averaging intervals into five blocks of three (i.e., block 1: 1-3, block 2: 4-6, block 3: 7-9, block 4: 10-12 and block 5: 13-15). All perceptual data are expressed as raw values due to there being no significant differences at baseline. Data distribution was assessed via a Shapiro-Wilk test. A parametric within-subject two-way analysis of variance was used to investigate the main effect of condition (HYP versus NOR and CON), time (baseline versus Post0, Post30 and Post60 or block 1 versus 2, 3, 4 and 5) and the condition × time interaction for normally distributed data. Partial eta-squared ( 2 ) was calculated as a measure of effect size. Values of 0.01, 0.06 and above 0.14 were considered as small, medium and large, respectively. Bonferroni post-hoc pairwise comparisons were used to identify locations of significant effects. Statistical testing was carried out in SPSS (v21, IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA). Data was considered significant if p ≤ 0.05. All data are presented as group means ± SD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head><p>Treadmill speed was slower during blocks 4 and 5 (-1.7 ± 0.1% and -2.2 ± 0.2%, respectively; p &lt; 0.05) in HYP versus NOR or CON (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>). HR increased progressively from block 1-5 in all conditions (+5.0 ± 0.5%, p = 0.011, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>). HR was higher overall during HYP compared to NOR and CON (+5.7 ± 1.0% and +10.0 ± 2.3%, respectively; p = 0.001). SpO 2 was lower throughout HYP (84.6 ± 0.8%) versus NOR and CON (97.3 ± 0.2% and 97.7 ± 0.3%, respectively; p = 0.001, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>). Compared to block 1, SpO 2 was also lower during blocks 2-5 in HYP only (p = 0.015).</p><p>Perceived recovery decreased progressively from block 1-5 (-11 ± 1%; p = 0.006, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>), irrespective of condition (p = 0.133). Perceived breathlessness increased progressively from block 1-5 (+9 ± 1%; p = 0.009, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref>), irrespective of condition (p = 0.323). Perceived limb discomfort was lower overall during HYP (-18 ± 3%; p = 0.003) compared to NOR, irrespective of time (p = 0.268), while failing to reach statistical significance during CON (-21 ± 6%, p = 0.060) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>). Perceived motivation and pleasure did not change throughout the protocol (all p &gt; 0.05; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref> and <ref type="figure">E</ref>).</p><p>Positive affect was lower at Post0 (-7 ± 1%), Post30 (-1 ± 0%) and Post60 (-4 ± 2%) compared to baseline (p = 0.020, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>). Positive affect was lower in HYP compared to NOR (-11 ± 6% and -6 ± 0%, respectively) and CON (-10 ± 1% and -1 ± 2%, respectively) at Post0 and Post30 time points (p = 0.004, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>). Negative affect decreased over time (-7 ± 2%; p = 0.038, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>). Perceived mood state improved over time (+26 ± 7%; p = 0.020, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>). Exercise self-efficacy was lower at Post0 after HYP versus NOR (-25 ± 5%; p = 0.044, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>Our novel findings show that a slower walking speed is adopted, along with lower limb discomfort and greater physiological stress (i.e., higher HR, lower SpO 2 ), in HYP compared with NOR. During CON -i.e., when the (hypoxic) speed is performed in normoxia -the level of physiological stress was lower than in HYP. Additionally, limb discomfort was lower in CON than in NOR. In overweightto-obese individuals, perceptually regulated interval walking in hypoxia at a lower external workload (i.e., walking speed) achieves a higher physiological stress compared to normoxia, yet with a lower perceived load (i.e., limb discomfort). Walking at the speed adopted in hypoxia produces similar psycho-physiological responses at the same absolute intensity in normoxia.</p><p>Throughout HYP (FiO 2 = 13.0%), greater physiological stress (i.e., higher HR, lower SpO 2 ) occurred compared to NOR and CON. These findings obtained in obese individuals are somewhat different to our previous work in trained runners, whereby HR did not differ between hypoxia (FiO 2 = 15.0%) and normoxia during perceptually regulated interval running (4 × 4 min running at RPE = 16, 3-min recoveries). <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> This may partly be due to larger hypoxia-related adjustments in workload (i.e., decreased treadmill speed) found in the previous (-6%) compared to the current study (-2%). In adults with obesity, Fernández Menéndez et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> showed that preferred walking speed increased each week during a 3-wks program, yet the treadmill speed selected by the hypoxic versus normoxic group only became significant lower by ∼9% in the last week of training. Pending confirmatory research, during a longitudinal training program using perceptually-regulated intervals, this walking gap between the two conditions could increase over time. Both Wiesner et al., <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> during 60-min continuous running/walking, and Chacaroun et al., <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> during interval cycling (15 × 1:1-min), have shown that lower hypoxia-induced absolute exercise level (i.e., speed/power) for a given exercise intensity (i.e., RPE or HR target) may preserve levels of physiological stress. In our study, in normoxia at a matched walking speed self-selected in hypoxia (CON), physiological stress level was reduced (i.e., lower HR, higher SpO 2 ), reinforcing the impact of hypoxia on increased physiological markers of stress observed in the current study.</p><p>Perceptions of limb discomfort were globally lower throughout HYP compared with NOR. This is unlike the findings of Christian et al., <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> who found greater perceived limb discomfort during 5 min continuous, sub-maximal perceptually regulated cycling (RPE 3 on CR10 Borg scale) in hypoxia (FiO 2 = 13.5%) versus normoxia. Remarkably, during HYP, this decrement also occurred prior to participants lowering the treadmill speed to maintain a preferred walking speed associated with an RPE of 14 as they walked intermittently. The current data suggests that, when walking in hypoxia (FiO 2 = 13.0%) at a perceptually regulated intensity, there may be a potential disconnection between overall RPE and the contribution of perceived limb discomfort to an RPE target of 14, that is not present when in normoxia. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> Interestingly, in the current study, the time-dependent changes in perceived recovery (decrease) and breathlessness (increase) did not differ between conditions, whilst perceived motivation and pleasure were maintained during perceptually regulated interval walking. Except for limb discomfort, which was also lower in CON than in NOR, there were no other significant differences between these conditions. This is important because slower walking speed in HYP but also in CON is perceived as more comfortable than in NOR and, thus, both conditions can limit joint mechanical stress and eventually reduce the risk of orthopaedic injury. However, only in HYP, slower walking speed is associated with increased physiological stress.</p><p>Positive affect and exercise self-efficacy were lower for up to 30 min after HYP compared with NOR and CON. This is in disagreement with the proposed hypothesis. It was postulated there would be matched exercise-related sensations between perceptually regulated interval walks at a slower speed in hypoxia versus normoxia, whilst exercise-related sensations would be greater in CON. Lower ratings of positive affect and exercise self-efficacy following HYP may be explained through the larger physiological stress experienced during interval walking compared to NOR and CON. Obese individuals are considered to be more perceptually sensitive to exercise-induced physiological stress than healthy individuals. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> Therefore, it could be argued that greater speed adjustments (i.e., decreases) in HYP versus NOR, potentiating matched exerciseinduced physiological stress, may have preserved exercise-related sensations after interval walking in the current study. However, time-dependent increases in perceived mood change and decreased negative affect occurred despite the effect of interval walking speed or hypoxic exposure. This is likely due to the positive effect of acute exercise on mood change, irrespective of intensity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref> Despite the decreases in interval walking speed during HYP, exercise-related sensations are negatively impacted for up to 30 min post-exercise compared with NOR and CON.</p><p>The present study has several limitations. A single hypoxic dose (FiO 2 = 13.0%) was implemented during hypoxic sessions based on current literature recommendations. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref> It is, however, unknown if this FiO 2 represents the threshold to induce a sufficient physiological stress, compared to normoxia, without negatively impacting performance of interval walking. Whether a lower FiO 2 permits performance aligned with greater expected physiological stress is also unclear. Perhaps a clamped SpO 2 compared to FiO 2 would be more beneficial in decreasing the inter-subject variability in psycho-physiological responses to the hypoxic stimulus. In doing so, two instruments -Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale (i.e., after the exercise session) and the Exercise Enjoyment Scale (i.e., during the exercise session) -should be considered for measuring the enjoyment responses. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref> The work:rest ratio employed in this study build on previous works, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> recommending shorter over longer interval walking cycles to maximise the psycho-physiological responses in obese individuals during hypoxic exposure. Further work should determine whether varying the hypoxic dose (i.e., severity and duration), interval exercise (i.e., duration) and intensity (i.e., perceptually regulated target RPE) leads to more favourable acute psycho-physiological responses when carried out in hypoxia compared to normoxia. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>Overweight individuals, or those with obesity, achieved a higher physiological stress during perceptually regulated (RPE = 14) interval walking in hypoxia at a progressively slower speed compared to normoxia, which was also perceived as less uncomfortable in their legs. Although exercise-related sensations were negatively impacted after perceptually regulated interval walking in hypoxia compared to normoxia (i.e., perceived mood change and exercise self-efficacy), these findings add to the acute, therapeutic benefits of hypoxic training for obese individuals. Finally, walking at the speed adopted in hypoxia produces similar psycho-physiological responses at the same absolute intensity in normoxia.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Treadmill speed (A), heart rate (B) and arterial oxygen saturation (SpO2; C) during the interval walking session. Data are condensed into five blocks for every three 2-min intervals and presented as mean ± SD. ANOVA main effects of condition, time and interaction are stated along with partial-eta squared for effect size into brackets with significant effects (p &lt; 0.05) highlighted in bold. Black bars = self-paced hypoxic condition (HYP); white bars = self-paced normoxic condition (NOR); grey bars = normoxic condition imposed with speed selected in hypoxic condition (CON). 1 and 2 denotes a statistically significant difference (p &lt; 0.05) between HYP versus NOR and CON, respectively. a denotes a statistically significant difference (p &lt; 0.05) compared to block 1.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,117.15,55.37,361.20,327.17" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Perceived recovery (A), motivation (B), breathlessness (C), limb discomfort (D) and pleasure (E) during the interval walking session. Data are condensed into five blocks for every three 2-min intervals and rest periods, and presented as mean ± SD. ANOVA main effects of condition, time and interaction are stated along with partial-eta squared for effect size into brackets with significant effects (P &lt; 0.05) highlighted in bold. Black bars = self-paced hypoxic condition (HYP); white bars = self-paced normoxic condition (NOR); grey bars = normoxic condition imposed with speed selected in hypoxic condition (CON). 1 and 3 denote a statistically significant difference (p &lt; 0.05) for HYP versus NOR and CON versus NOR, respectively. a denotes a statistically significant difference (p &lt; 0.05) compared to block 1.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,117.14,55.31,361.20,478.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Perceived mood change (A), positive affect (B), exercise self-efficacy (C) and negative affect (D) assessed at baseline and 0 (Post0), 30 (Post30) and 60 (Post60) min after the interval walking session. Data are presented as absolute change from baseline and as mean ± SD. ANOVA main effects of condition, time and interaction are stated along with partial-eta squared for effect size into brackets with significant effects (p &lt; 0.05) highlighted in bold. Black bars = self-paced hypoxic condition (HYP); white bars = self-paced normoxic condition (NOR); grey bars = normoxic condition imposed with speed selected in hypoxic condition (CON). 1 and 2 denotes a statistically significant difference (p &lt; 0.05) between HYP versus NOR and CON, respectively. * and ** denote a statistically significant difference (p &lt; 0.05) compared to baseline and post0, respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,81.65,56.01,432.00,246.53" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			
			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>There is no source of funding to declare. The results of this study are presented clearly, honestly, and without fabrication, falsification, or inappropriate data manipulation.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Obesity: definition, comorbidities, causes, and burden</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Apovian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Manag Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="176" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Apovian C. Obesity: definition, comorbidities, causes, and burden. Am J Manag Care 2016; 22(7):s176-185.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The incidence of co-morbidities related to obesity and overweight: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Guh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bansback</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">88</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Guh D, Zhang W, Bansback N et al. The incidence of co-morbidities related to obe- sity and overweight: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Public Health 2019; 9:88.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energetic cost and preferred speed of walking in obese vs. normal weight women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Browning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kram</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obes Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="891" to="899" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Browning R, Kram R. Energetic cost and preferred speed of walking in obese vs. normal weight women. Obes Res 2005; 13(5):891-899.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dose-response effect of walking exercise on weight loss. How much is enough?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1484" to="1493" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Brill J, Perry A, Parker L et al. Dose-response effect of walking exercise on weight loss. How much is enough? Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord 2002; 26(11):1484-1493.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lifestyle intervention of hypocaloric dieting and walking reduces abdominal obesity and improves coronary heart disease risk factors in obese, postmenopausal, African-American and Caucasian women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nicklas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Berman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="189" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nicklas B, Dennis K, Berman D et al. Lifestyle intervention of hypocaloric dieting and walking reduces abdominal obesity and improves coronary heart disease risk factors in obese, postmenopausal, African-American and Caucasian women. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci 2003; 58(2):181-189.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">STR-RIDE: a randomized, controlled study of exercise intensity and amount</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Slentz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Aiken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Houmard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1613" to="1618" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Inactivity, exercise, and visceral fat</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Slentz CA, Aiken LB, Houmard JA et al. Inactivity, exercise, and visceral fat. STR- RIDE: a randomized, controlled study of exercise intensity and amount. J Appl Physiol 2005; 99(4):1613-1618.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mysterious case of the public health guideline that is (almost) entirely ignored: call for a research agenda on the causes of the extreme avoidance of physical activity in obesity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ekkekakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vazou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bixby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obes Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="329" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ekkekakis P, Vazou S, Bixby R et al. The mysterious case of the public health guideline that is (almost) entirely ignored: call for a research agenda on the causes of the extreme avoidance of physical activity in obesity. Obes Rev 2016; 17(4):313-329.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Validation of the intensity of walking for pleasure in obese adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Byrne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wearing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prev Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hills A, Byrne N, Wearing S et al. Validation of the intensity of walking for pleasure in obese adults. Prev Med 2006; 42(1):47-50.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exercise does not feel the same when you are overweight: the impact of self-selected and imposed intensity on affect and exertion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ekkekakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lind</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Obes (Lond)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="652" to="660" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ekkekakis P, Lind E. Exercise does not feel the same when you are overweight: the impact of self-selected and imposed intensity on affect and exertion. Int J Obes (Lond) 2006; 30(4):652-660.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of short-term normobaric hypoxic walking training on energetics and mechanics of gait in adults with obesity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fern</forename><surname>Ández Men Éndez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Saudan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sperisen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obesity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="819" to="827" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fern ández Men éndez A, Saudan G, Sperisen L et al. Effects of short-term nor- mobaric hypoxic walking training on energetics and mechanics of gait in adults with obesity. Obesity 2018; 26(5):819-827.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The circulatory and metabolic responses to hypoxia in humans -with special reference to adipose tissue physiology and obesity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Heinonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Boushel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kalliokoski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Endocrinol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">116</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Heinonen I, Boushel R, Kalliokoski K. The circulatory and metabolic responses to hypoxia in humans -with special reference to adipose tissue physiology and obesity. Front Endocrinol 2016; 7:116.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Walking in hypoxia: an efficient treatment to lessen mechanical constraints and improve health in obese individuals?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Girard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Malatesta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Millet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">73</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Girard O, Malatesta D, Millet GP. Walking in hypoxia: an efficient treatment to lessen mechanical constraints and improve health in obese individuals? Front Physiol 2017; 8:73.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Physiological responses to hypoxic constant-load and high-intensity interval exercise sessions in healthy subjects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chacaroun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Flore</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">199</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chacaroun S, Gonzalez I, Flore P et al. Physiological responses to hypoxic constant-load and high-intensity interval exercise sessions in healthy subjects. Eur J Appl Physiol 2019; 199(1):123-134.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psycho-physiological responses to perceptually-regulated interval runs in hypoxia and normoxia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hobbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Gaoua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiol Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">209</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112611</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hobbins L, Gaoua N, Hunter S et al. Psycho-physiological responses to perceptually-regulated interval runs in hypoxia and normoxia. Physiol Behav 2019; 209:112611.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acute psychophysiological responses to cyclic variation of intermittent hypoxic exposure in adults with obesity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hobbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Girard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Gaoua</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">High Alti Med Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="270" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hobbins L, Girard O, Gaoua N et al. Acute psychophysiological responses to cyclic variation of intermittent hypoxic exposure in adults with obesity. High Alti Med Biol 2019; 20(3):262-270.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of age and physical activity status on the speed-aerobic demand relationship of walking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rothstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Larish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="200" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Martin P, Rothstein D, Larish D. Effects of age and physical activity status on the speed-aerobic demand relationship of walking. J Appl Physiol 1992; 73(1):200-206.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A practical approach to monitoring recovery: development of a perceived recovery status scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Laurent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bishop</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Strength Cond Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="620" to="628" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Laurent C, Green J, Bishop P et al. A practical approach to monitoring recovery: development of a perceived recovery status scale. J Strength Cond Res 2011; 25(3):620-628.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal associations between individual changes in hormones, training motivation and physical performance in elite and non-elite trained men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Crewther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Carruthers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kilduff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol Sport</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Crewther B, Carruthers J, Kilduff L et al. Temporal associations between individual changes in hormones, training motivation and physical per- formance in elite and non-elite trained men. Biol Sport 2016; 33(3): 215-221.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of peripheral and central chemoreflex activation on the isopnoeic rating of breathing in exercising humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Whipp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">411</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ward S, Whipp B. Effects of peripheral and central chemoreflex activation on the isopnoeic rating of breathing in exercising humans. J Physiol 1989; 411:27-43.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Not what, but how one feels: the measurement of affect during exercise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rejeski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Sport Exerc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="304" to="317" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hardy CJ, Rejeski WJ. Not what, but how one feels: the measurement of affect during exercise. J Sport Exerc Psychol 1989; 11:304-317.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and validation of brief measures of positive and negative affect: the PANAS scales</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tellegen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pers Soc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1063" to="1070" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Watson D, Clark L, Tellegen A. Development and validation of brief measures of positive and negative affect: the PANAS scales. J Pers Soc Psychol 1988; 54(6):1063-1070.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Measurement in sport and exercise psychology. Making sense of words and stories in qualitative research-strategies and consideration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sparkes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tenenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Human Kinetics</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Champaign, IL</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Smith B, Sparkes A, Tenenbaum G et al. Measurement in sport and exercise psy- chology. Making sense of words and stories in qualitative research-strategies and consideration, Champaign, IL, Human Kinetics, 2012.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influences of normobaric hypoxia training on physical fitness and metabolic risk markers in overweight to obese subjects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wiesner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haufe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Engeli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obesity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="116" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wiesner S, Haufe S, Engeli S et al. Influences of normobaric hypoxia training on physical fitness and metabolic risk markers in overweight to obese subjects. Obesity 2009; 18(1):116-120.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of ratings of perceived exertion during self-paced exercise: what are we actually measuring</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Abbiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Peiffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Meeusen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sports Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1235" to="1243" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Abbiss C, Peiffer J, Meeusen R et al. Role of ratings of perceived exertion dur- ing self-paced exercise: what are we actually measuring? Sports Med 2015; 45(9):1235-1243.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of sense of effort on self-selected cycling power output</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Christian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bishop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Girard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">115</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Christian R, Bishop D, Girard O et al. The role of sense of effort on self-selected cycling power output. Front Physiol 2014; 5:115.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of exercise intensity for improving depressed mood in depression: a dose-response study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Koltyn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stegner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behav Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="537" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Meyer J, Koltyn K, Stegner A et al. Influence of exercise intensity for improv- ing depressed mood in depression: a dose-response study. Behav Ther 2016; 47(4):527-537.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Therapeutic potential of intermittent hypoxia: a matter of dose</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Navarrete-Opazo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">307</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1181" to="1197" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Navarrete-Opazo A, Mitchell G. Therapeutic potential of intermittent hypoxia: a matter of dose. Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol 2014; 307(10):R1181-1197.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Affective and enjoyment responses in high intensity interval training and continuous training: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Brr</forename><surname>Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kilpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">197124</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Oliveira BRR, Santos TM, Kilpatrick M et al. Affective and enjoyment responses in high intensity interval training and continuous training: a systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS One 2018; 13(6):e0197124.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
