<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Hot water immersion: Maintaining core body temperature above 38.5°C mitigates muscle fatigue</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Benoît</forename><surname>Sautillet</surname></persName>
							<email>benoit.sautillet@u-picardie.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Sport Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">APERE Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Picardie Jules Verne</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3300</postCode>
									<settlement>Amiens</settlement>
									<region>UR</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nicolas</forename><surname>Bourdillon</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Sport Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Lausanne</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lausanne</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Grégoire</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Millet</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Sport Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Lausanne</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lausanne</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">|</forename><forename type="middle">Fréderic</forename><surname>Lemaître</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Sport Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CETAPS Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3832</postCode>
									<region>UR</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Maryne</forename><surname>Cozette</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-8211-7151</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Sport Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">APERE Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Picardie Jules Verne</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3300</postCode>
									<settlement>Amiens</settlement>
									<region>UR</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stéphane</forename><surname>Delanaud</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR_I 01 laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">PériTox</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CURS- UPJV</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-80054</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">|</forename><surname>Saïd Ahmaïdi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Sport Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">APERE Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Picardie Jules Verne</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3300</postCode>
									<settlement>Amiens</settlement>
									<region>UR</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">|</forename><surname>Guillaume Costalat</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Sport Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">APERE Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Picardie Jules Verne</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3300</postCode>
									<settlement>Amiens</settlement>
									<region>UR</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Guillaume</forename><surname>Costalat</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-0478-2882</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Normandy University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Rouen</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Picardie Jules Verne</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Amiens</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution">avenue Paul Claudel</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Amiens cedex 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>80025</postCode>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Hot water immersion: Maintaining core body temperature above 38.5°C mitigates muscle fatigue</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F1F190FC9A2405176E28D2DD11A9E6A8</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/sms.14503</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 28 March 2023 | Revised: 6 September 2023 | Accepted: 15 September 2023</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2026-03-22T22:09+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">b64991a</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Benoît Sautillet</term>
					<term>laboratoire &quot;Adaptations Physiologiques à l&apos;Exercice et Réadaptation à l&apos;Effort&quot; (APERE</term>
					<term>UR 3300)</term>
					<term>UFR STAPS</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Purpose: Hot water immersion (HWI) has gained popularity to promote muscle recovery, despite limited data on the optimal heat dose. The purpose of this study was to compare the responses of two exogenous heat strains on core body temperature, hemodynamic adjustments, and key functional markers of muscle recovery following exercise-induced muscle damage (EIMD).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>: Twenty-eight physically active males completed an individually tailored EIMD protocol immediately followed by one of the following recovery interventions: HWI (40°C, HWI 40 ), HWI (41°C, HWI 41 ) or warm water immersion (36°C, CON 36 ). Gastrointestinal temperature (T gi ), hemodynamic adjustments (cardiac output [CO], mean arterial pressure [MAP], and systemic vascular resistance [SVR]), pre-frontal cortex deoxyhemoglobin (HHb), ECG-derived respiratory frequency, and subjective perceptual measures were tracked throughout immersion. In addition, functional markers of muscle fatigue (maximal concentric peak torque [T peak ]) and muscle damage (late-phase rate of force development [RFD 100-200 ]) were measured prior to EIMD (pre-), 24 h (post-24 h), and 48 h (post-48 h) post-EIMD. Results: By the end of immersion, HWI 41 led to significantly higher T gi values than HWI 40 (38.8 ± 0.1 vs. 38.0°C ± 0.6°C, p &lt; 0.001). While MAP was well maintained throughout immersion, only HWI 41 led to increased (HHb) (+4.2 ± 1.47 μM; p = 0.005) and respiratory frequency (+4.0 ± 1.21 breath.min -1 ; p = 0.032). Only HWI 41 mitigated the decline in RFD 100-200 at post-24 h (-7.1 ± 31.8%; p = 0.63) and T peak at post-48 h (-3.1 ± 4.3%, p = 1). Conclusion: In physically active males, maintaining a core body temperature of ~25 min within the range of 38.5°C-39°C has been found to be effective in improving muscle recovery, while minimizing the risk of excessive physiological heat strain. K E Y W O R D S exercise-induced muscle damage, hemodynamic adjustments, heat dose, muscle recovery, prefrontal cortex oxygenation, recovery intervention F I G U R E 1 Timeline of the experimental design. See text for acronyms.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">| INTRODUCTION</head><p>Exercise-induced muscle damage (EIMD) is a transient phenomenon characterized by structural damage to myofibers and symptoms occurring both immediately and for up to 14 days after the initial bout. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> As a result, EIMD is often associated with decreased muscle function (i.e., muscle fatigue) and reduced range of joint motion together with the occurrence of delayed onset muscle soreness (DOMS). <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> In athletes, EIMD monitoring is crucial given its potential to impair performance while increasing the likelihood of injuries. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> A significant concern for many athletes is the ability to recover from EIMD to prime their body for future events. Therefore, athletes who require rapid recovery between bouts of damaging exercise should implement evidence-based recovery strategies to enhance muscle recovery process.</p><p>Recovery interventions involving muscle temperature manipulation are believed to improve post-exercise recovery, with cryotherapy being especially popular among athletes and coaches. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Often claimed for its antiinflammatory properties, the use of cryotherapy to accelerate the recovery of muscle function is nowadays challenged. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> In addition, cold water immersion was shown to be as effective-but not better-than a sham condition on muscle recovery, thus questioning the relevance of this strategy. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> Conversely, thermotherapy in the form of passive hot water immersion (HWI), hot waterperfused cuff, microwave diathermy, sauna, or heat pad have gained interest as a way to promote muscle recovery, despite current limited data. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> In healthy humans, a single bout of thermotherapy with prior exerciseinduced fatigue led to immediate improvement in both contractile and neuromuscular function. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> Conversely, in the late recovery phase from muscle fatigue or EIMD (i.e., from post-24 h to post-72 h), contrasting outcomes have been observed on functional recovery, muscle damage (creatine kinase and lactate dehydrogenase), or markers relevant to DOMS. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> Exercise is a physiological stress factor known to upregulate heat shock proteins (HSP), including the superfamily HSP70. In the hours and days following EIMD, an accumulation of HSP70 within the muscle has been observed. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> Recent evidence suggests that these molecular chaperones play a key role in muscle regeneration process in response to muscle damage/injury. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> In humans, heat stress per se also appears to promote a heat shock response. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> Taken together, heat may act as a potent exogenous stress to promote HSP accumulation and thus muscle regeneration. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> However, an increase in core temperature does not systematically coincide with HSP accumulation as evidenced in the study by Fuchs and colleagues showing that a significant but modest rise in core temperature (~+0.6°C from baseline) had no effect on HSP expression. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> In the above-mentioned studies that failed to show clear benefits of thermotherapy, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> it is worth noting that the temperature used was within the range of 36°C-39°C with immersion time from 10 to 30 min, thus preventing any significant rise in core body temperature and subsequent heat shock response.</p><p>Although guidelines have recently emerged in the management of sports event in the heat, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> there is currently no recommendation on the heat dose for recovery purposes. Many of the previous studies relied on passive HWI with the expectation of an improved functional recovery, presumably for its convenience on the field and lower cost compared with other heat-based therapies. For instance, Sabapathy and colleagues found that HWI mitigates the decline in short-term muscle strength and soreness in healthy humans. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> However, their heat-based protocolwhole-body HWI at 42°C for 45 min-induced a rapid rise in core body temperature up to 39.4°C (≳+2°C), likely explaining the substantial thermal discomfort experienced by the participants. In some cases, these perceptions were further associated with adverse symptoms (e.g., nausea and dizziness) fairly similar to those reported with milder forms of heat-related illness. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> Taken together, the existing literature suggests a potential dose-response relationship, where low-to-moderate levels of immersion temperature (36°C-39°C) may have limited effects on muscle recovery, while a more severe immersion temperature (42°C) could yield beneficial outcomes. Based on these findings, it remains to be determined whether an optimal immersion temperature within the range of 39°C and 42°C exists, which can maintain muscular benefits while minimizing the occurrence of clinical symptoms associated with excessive rise in core body temperature. In a previous work, comparison of thermal responses to immersion demonstrated that HWI at 40°C induced a modest rise in core body temperature as opposed to immersion at 41.5°C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> This suggests that HWI at 40°C may not offer an adequate stimulus to effectively promote accelerated muscle recovery. However, an investigation is warranted to elucidate whether two closely spaced temperatures elicit divergent effects on muscle recovery.</p><p>Titrating the optimal heat dose is also crucial to preserve the health of athletes, particularly with regard to maintaining the integrity of the brain. The significant rise in core body temperature (≳+2°C) observed in the study by Sabapathy and colleagues is expected to be safe for the brain parenchyma. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> However, recent evidence suggests that such a rise in core body temperature may temporarily disrupt the balance of cerebral metabolic supply and demand, as a consequence of reduced cerebral blood flow. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> The resulting decrease in brain oxygen delivery may worsen orthostatic intolerance, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> posing a potential risk when athletes stand up to exit the bath. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> The objective of the present study was to assess the effects of a bearable, practical (lasting &lt;1 h; limiting cardiovascular strain and excessive rise in core body temperature toward thresholds associated with adverse symptoms) and evidence-based heat protocol. Therefore, the main aim of this study was to quantitatively compare, following EIMD, the effects of two close exogenous heat strains (40°C, HWI 40 , and 41°C, HWI 41 ) on key functional markers of muscle recovery. In addition, gastrointestinal temperature, hemodynamic adjustments, pre-frontal cortex oxygenation, ECG-derived respiratory frequency, and perceptual measures were tracked throughout HWI. We hypothesized that both HWI modalities would increase heat and cardiovascular strain, with HWI 41 but not HWI 40 mitigating EIMD-induced decline in strength parameters and soreness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">| MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">| Participants</head><p>Thirty healthy males (age: 20.5 ± 2.0 years old; body mass: 69.5 ± 11.2 kg; height: 176.9 ± 6.8 cm) were recruited and split into three groups: HWI 41 (41°C, n = 10), HWI 40 (40°C, n = 10), and CON 36 (36°C, n = 10). Participants were physically active men (&gt;10 h of training per week), familiar with resistance-type exercise and EIMD with no current illness, no history of lower limb musculoskeletal injuries and no past or present respiratory/cardiac disorders. Participants were asked to refrain from exercising or using any additional recovery strategy throughout the protocol. All individuals completed a medical history, an exercise questionnaire, and a written informed consent to participate. The study received institutional ethical approval and was conducted in accordance with the 1964 Helsinki declaration and its later amendments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">| Experimental design</head><p>Our single-blind, parallel-group, randomized controlled study was designed to primarily compare the effects of two close water temperatures (40°C and 41°C) on key markers of muscle recovery. As depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>, participants visited the laboratory on three consecutive days. Day 1 consisted of assessing baseline measures (pre-) as well as to complete the standardized EIMD protocol. Immediately following EIMD, participants were randomly allocated to one of the following recovery interventions: HWI 41 , HWI 40 , or CON 36 . The CON 36 was considered as the sham intervention since this hot water temperature is not expected to significantly increase core body temperature. In the next two visits (post-24 h and post-48 h), the same variables as in Day 1 were measured using the same methodology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">| Immersion protocol</head><p>Hot water recovery consisted of immersion in an inflatable bath (Novarden, NetSpa Poolstar, France) to the waist level, seated, legs fully extended and forearms non-submerged. Immersion up to the waist level was preferred to whole-body immersion to maximize participants' adherence to the protocol. Water temperature was continuously checked (every 5 min) by means of a water thermometer. If required, hot water coming from the tap (45°C) was used to maintain the target temperature (±0.1°C) and drained meanwhile to ensure its level was kept up to the waist. Participants were invited to drink water (~1 L) throughout immersion and following the bath, a fluid ingestion equivalent to 120% of body mass loss. During HWI 40 and HWI 41 , termination criteria for the immersion included either one of the following: (i) gastrointestinal temperature ≥ 39°C since higher temperature than 39°C may lead to significant heat exhaustion-like symptoms 24 ; (ii) blood pressure thresholds associated with presyncope, that is, a drop in systolic or diastolic of &gt;20 mmHg or 10 mmHg, respectively; (iii) fatigue, dizziness, palpitations, visual or hearing disturbances, nausea, neck, or back discomfort, and (iv) thermal sensation or thermal comfort rated on the visual scale as "extremely hot" or "extremely uncomfortable," respectively. Unlike relying on termination criteria, the immersion time during CON 36 was determined prior to the initiation of the session. This approach was chosen due to the expectation of negligible changes in core body temperature, blood pressure, or subjective markers. Specifically, the immersion time for CON 36 was aligned with the mean duration observed during the pre-experimental phase of HWI 40 and HWI 41 (~38 min). No information about the water temperature nor the research hypothesis was given to the participants to avoid any sham effect.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">| Gastrointestinal temperature</head><p>Throughout the recovery interventions, gastrointestinal temperature (T gi ) was sampled every 30 s using an ingestible telemetric temperature capsule system (e-Celsius, BodyCap). The e-Celcius system has shown to provide good agreement in vivo compared with rectal temperature during exercise-heat stress. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> The capsule was ingested more than 6 h prior to onset of the recovery intervention. Prior to water immersion, participants were invited to drink a small amount of cold water to establish whether the sensor had departed the stomach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">| Thermal impulse and physiological strain index calculation</head><p>Two metrics were used to quantitatively estimate the endogenous heat dose experienced by the participants during the two conditions (HWI 41 and HWI 40 ). The thermal impulse represents the area under the curve when core body temperature exceeds 38.5°C, calculated as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref> :</p><p>where T i&gt;38.5 is the thermal impulse (°.min), that is, the area under the curve when T gi exceeds 38.5°C; T gi-i is the gastrointestinal temperature at any time i; T gi-38.5 is the gastrointestinal temperature at 38.5°C; dt is the duration of each recovery intervention.</p><p>In addition, the highest physiological heat strain experienced by the participants during immersion was calculated as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref> :</p><p>where PSI is the physiological strain index (AU); T gi (zenith) and HR (zenith) are the highest gastrointestinal temperature and heart rate experienced by the participants, respectively; T gi (0) and HR (0) are baseline T gi and HR, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">| Isokinetic dynamometer and data acquisition</head><p>The EIMD protocol and assessment of quadriceps femoris function were both performed by means of an isokinetic dynamometer (Cybex Norm®, division of Lumex, Inc.). Before testing, participants followed a standardized warm-up made up of 7 min of cycling at 75 W in addition to three warm-up contractions on the dynamometer. Participants were seated in an upright position and then fastened using straps to secure the chest, hip, and ankle (level arm) of the dominant (working) leg. The lateral epicondyle of the knee joint was aligned with the dynamometer's axis of rotation. Raw dynamometer signals (torque, angular displacement, and velocity) were recorded at 1000 Hz with a PowerLab-16/35 data acquisition system and later analyzed with the LabChart Pro software package (version 8.1, ADInstruments). Prior to data analysis, raw data were filtered (low-pass: 10 Hz) and resampled to 100 Hz.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">T i&gt;38.5 = ∫ T gi-i -T gi-38.5 dt PSI = 5 • T gi (zenith) -T gi (0) 39.5 -T gi (0) + 5 • HR (zenith) -HR(0) 180 -HR(0)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7">| Exercise-induced muscle damage</head><p>An individually tailored EIMD protocol was chosen given the wide inter-individual response to a standardized eccentric bout. Therefore, our primary criterion to assess EIMD was based on force-generating capacity rather than a predefined number (sets) of eccentric contractions.</p><p>A moderate reduction in force-generating capacity was considered in the present study, that is, a 20% to 30% loss in maximal concentric peak torque (T peak ) from baseline values. This range has been chosen to ensure significant impairment in muscle strength and pronounced elevation in DOMS-related pain up until the last reassessment of muscle function, that is, post-48 h. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref> Briefly, all participants first completed five sets of 10 maximal unilateral, isokinetic (30°.s -1 ), eccentric contractions with their quadriceps femoris muscle. The range of motion was set from 0° (full knee extension) to 90° knee flexion for all participants. Then, participants were asked to complete a single set of three maximal, isokinetic, concentric knee extension at 002E60°.s -1 , with the best trial retained to assess reduction in T peak . If strength loss criterion was not met, two to four sets of 10 maximal eccentric contractions were proposed until strength loss reached a value &gt;20%. To limit possible muscle injuries, participants were limited to 90 eccentric contractions. During each contraction, participants were verbally encouraged to resist the movement maximally throughout the full range of motion while having real-time visual feedback of their performance on a computer screen. At the completion of each eccentric contraction, the leg was immediately returned passively to the starting position and another eccentric contraction was immediately initiated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8">| Assessment of muscle function and soreness</head><p>In the three conditions, all measurements were assessed at baseline (pre-) and daily throughout the recovery period (post-24 h and post-48 h) as outlined in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>. Two sets of three maximal, concentric knee extension were performed at a slow isokinetic angular velocity (60°. s -1 ) to measure T peak (Nm). The two sets were separated by a 2-min passive recovery. Among the six concentric contractions, the highest T peak value was retained for further analysis. The intra-individual coefficient of variation of this test was &lt;10%.</p><p>In addition, the concentric contraction that produced the highest T peak value was used to calculate the rate of force development (RFD), a more representative indirect marker of muscle damage than T peak . <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> Given its high reliability and sensitivity to EIMD, the late-phase RFD (RFD 100-200 , N.s -1 ) was preferred to its early phase (e.g., RFD 0-50 ). RFD 100-200 was determined as the slope of the force vs. time curve (Δforce/Δtime) within time intervals of 100-200 ms relative to onset of contraction. Onset of muscle contraction was defined as the instant when the knee extensor force exceeded the baseline force by 7.5 N.</p><p>Pressure pain threshold (PPT) was assessed by means of a hand-held digital algometer (FDX-50, Wagner Instruments) to quantify the recovery from DOMS. The pressure (N.cm -2 ) was applied gradually and perpendicularly to midbelly sites of the vastus lateralis. A 1-cm 2 hard rubber tip was used to apply the pressure. The first point at which the first painful sensation was felt by the subject corresponded to PPT. At each time point, three consecutive measurements were done by a single trained examiner (BS) and then averaged for further analysis. For a given subject, a total of nine measurements were done on the same muscle site. Given that each PPT test itself produces exogenous (artificial) pain, a carry-over effect may have occurred throughout the protocol; thus, bilateral measurements (i.e., measures of the control and the tired leg) were performed to ensure that any changes in PPT values were attributable to the recovery intervention.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.9">| Hemodynamic measurements</head><p>Participants were first seated in a neutral room to record a 5-min resting period of physiological and perceptual responses, referred hereafter and in the graphs as the "resting" phase. Cardiac output (CO), stroke volume (SV), and heart rate (HR) were continuously tracked by bio-impedance (PhysioFlow PF-05, Manatec Biomedical) throughout immersion and post-immersion. After shaving and applying a mildly abrasive paste (NuPrep) to the skin, two sets of electrodes, one transmitting and the other receiving, were applied above the supraclavicular fossa (left side) and along the xiphoid process. Another pair of electrodes was used to measure a single electrocardiogram signal (ECG). Electrode contact with the skin was protected from humidity and sweat with adhesive films (Tegaderm™) to preserve the impedance signal.</p><p>Simultaneously, systolic (SBP) and diastolic (DBP) blood pressure were measured every 5 min by means of an automatic digital blood pressure monitor (Omron M7 Intelli IT, Omron Healthcare). Mean arterial pressure (MAP) was then obtained from blood pressure recordings, taking into account the increased time dominance of the systolic phase with increasing HR, as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> :</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">MAP = DBP + 0.01 • e 4.14-40.74 HR • PP</formula><p>where MAP is the mean arterial pressure (mmHg); DBP is the diastolic blood pressure (mmHg); HR is the heart rate (beat.min -1 ) and PP is the pulse pressure, that is, SBP minus DBP (mmHg).</p><p>Finally, systemic vascular resistance (SVR) was obtained as follows, considering the central venous pressure negligible:</p><p>where SVR is the systemic vascular resistance (dyne.s.cm -5 ); MAP is the mean arterial pressure (mmHg) and CO is the cardiac output (L.min -1 ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.10">| ECG-derived respiratory frequency</head><p>A MATLAB-based package provided by Physio Flow's designers was applied to extract ECG recording of each subject. ECG sampling rate was 250 Hz. ECG-derived respiratory frequency (EDR, breath.min -1 ) is a common and well-accepted technique, for review see. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> Briefly, EDR was computed on successive windows of 5 min sliding by 1 min. R and S peaks were identified on the ECG trace and two cubic spline interpolation were performed for the R series and the S series respectively. Amplitude was computed as the difference between the R spline and the S spline. Respiration frequency was estimated from amplitude using a fast Fourier transform (fft, Hamming window, and Welch periodogram) on each window separately.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.11">| Peripheral oxygenation saturation and pre-frontal cortex oxygenation</head><p>Peripheral oxygen saturation (SpO 2 ) was recorded every 5 min in the bath with a finger probe oximeter (Zuddo YM101). Simultaneously, pre-frontal cortex oxygenation was assessed continuously using a continuous-wave Near InfraRed Spectrometer (NIRS, Oxymon MK III, Artinis Medical Systems BV). The probe was placed over the forehead, wrapped into a black light-absorbing cloth, and secured with a tenser bandage (around the head) to prevent probe movement and contamination from extraneous light. The NIRS probe setup consisted of one receiver and two transmitters (LED light sources) placed in a row with a source-detector distance of 35 and 45 mm. Each transmitter provides two lights at 857 and 764 nm that are mostly sensitive to changes in oxy-([HbO 2 ]) and deoxyhemoglobin ([HHb]) concentrations, respectively. In the present study, only [HHb] is reported as this NIRS-derived variable appears less sensitive to local blood flow than [HbO 2 ]. The contribution ratio of the cerebral tissue to the optical signals increases as the source-detector distance widens. Therefore, only [HHb] arising from the source-detector of 45 mm (penetration depth of ~22.5 mm) was considered for further analysis. The differential path-length factor (DPF) was adjusted for each participant. Our NIRS device relies on a continuous-wave technology (i.e., constant DPF), preventing determination of absolute values of [HHb]. Therefore, values are reported as a delta relative to resting values in units of micromolar (μM). The raw data were recorded at a sampling rate of 10 Hz and subsequently downsampled to a rate of 1 Hz for further analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.12">| Thermal sensation and thermal comfort</head><p>Every 5 min into the bath, thermal sensation was assessed using a modified perceptual scale where -5 denotes for "extremely cold," 0 "neutral" and +5 "extremely hot." Similarly, thermal comfort was measured using a modified perceptual scale where 1 denotes for "comfortable" and 5 "extremely uncomfortable."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.13">| Statistical analysis</head><p>A prospective power analysis was used to calculate the required sample size (G*Power software version 3.1). In the present study, a change in T peak across a repeated measure (within-between interaction) was considered as the key outcome variable. The partial eta-squared (η p = 0.142) from Sabapathy et al. (2021) was used to calculate the sample size. Based on an assumption of type I error of 0.05, type II error of 0.05 (i.e., power of 95%) and considering a drop-out rate of 20%, 10 participants per group (n = 30) were required to determine whether changes were significant.</p><p>The samples were first tested for normality, homogeneity of variance, and sphericity with Shapiro-Wilk's, Levene's, and Mauchly's test, respectively. If Mauchly's test was significant, the degrees of freedom were corrected using Greenhouse-Geisser estimates of sphericity. One-way ANOVA with repeated measures was conducted to compare key markers of muscle recovery (T peak , RFD 100-200 , and PPT) across recovery time points (pre-vs. post-24 h vs. post-48 h). Throughout immersion, repeated measures one-way ANOVA was used to track changes in T gi , hemodynamic parameters, [HHb], EDR, SpO 2 , and thermal comfort/sensation. Two-way between-within ANOVA was conducted to compare the above-mentioned variables between the three conditions (between factor) across time points (within factor). Multiple pairwise comparisons adjusted with the Bonferroni correction were conducted whenever the main effect was significant. Statistical analysis and graphing were performed using JASP (version 0.16.10, JASP team, 2022) and OriginPro software (version 2019b, Origin-Lab), respectively. Statistical significance for all analyses was accepted at p &lt; 0.05. Effect sizes associated with ANOVA (omega-squared, ω 2 ) and subsequent particular comparison (Cohen's d) are reported in the results section. Changes reported in the results section refer to means ± SD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">| RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">| EIMD-induced muscle fatigue</head><p>Two participants were removed from analysis since they did not satisfy strength loss criterion (i.e., a drop in T peak &lt; 20% post-EIMD) despite 90 eccentric contractions. Among the remaining participants (n = 28), EIMD induced a similar acute muscle fatigue (i.e., drop in T peak values) across the three conditions (CON 36 : -21.6 ± 4.5%; HWI 41 : -20.3 ± 7.5%; HWI 40 : -26.4 ± 5.6%; p = 0.164) (Figure <ref type="figure">2A</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">| Markers of muscle recovery (T peak , RFD 100-200 , and PPT)</head><p>Changes in T peak and RFD 100-200 in response to the three conditions are displayed in Figure <ref type="figure">2A</ref>,<ref type="figure">B</ref>. One-way repeated measures ANOVA revealed a significant effect of condition on T peak across recovery time points (CON 36 : F (2,14) = 15.57; p &lt; 0.01; ω 2 = 0.40; HWI 41 : F (2,12) = 7.79; p = 0.007; ω 2 = 0.04; HWI 40 : F (2,12) = 21.97; p &lt; 0.001; ω 2 = 0.19). More precisely, T peak significantly dropped at post-24 h and post-48 h in response to CON 36 and HWI 40 (all p &lt; 0.05). Conversely, while T peak was significantly depressed at post-24 h in response to HWI 41 (p = 0.008; d = 0.48), no difference was observed at post-48 h when compared to baseline values (p = 1; d = 0.13). One-way repeated measures ANOVA revealed a significant effect of CON 36 (F (2,14) = 5.04; p = 0.022; ω 2 = 0.14) and HWI 40 (F (2,12) = 4.69; p = 0.031; ω 2 = 0.12) on RFD 100-200 across recovery time points. More precisely, at any recovery time points, RFD 100-200 significantly dropped in response to these two conditions (all p &lt; 0.05). Conversely, no significant main effect of HWI 41 on RFD 100-200 was observed across recovery time points (F (2,12) = 0.47; p = 0.63; ω 2 = 0).</p><p>Changes in PPT in response to the three conditions are presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref>. For the control leg, neither CON 36 , HWI 40, nor HWI 41 had a significant effect on PPT (all p &gt; 0.05). For the tired leg, one-way repeated measures ANOVA revealed a significant effect of CON 36 (F (2,14) = 17.18; p &lt; 0.01; ω 2 = 0.15), HWI 41 (F (2,12) = 6.37; p = 0.013; ω 2 = 0.16), and HWI 40 (F (2,12) = 11.11; p = 0.002; ω 2 = 0.41) on PPT across recovery time points. More precisely, at any recovery time points, PPT significantly dropped in response to CON 36 and HWI 40 (all p &lt; 0.05). Conversely, while PPT was significantly reduced at post-24 h in response to HWI 41 (p = 0.027; d = 1.01), no difference was observed at post-48 h when compared to baseline values (p = 0.970; d = 0.01).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">| Exogenous and endogenous heat doses</head><p>Exogenous and endogenous heat doses experienced by the participants throughout CON 36 , HWI 41 , and HWI 40 are displayed in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. Termination criteria were achieved slightly earlier during HWI 40 compared with HWI 41 ; however, when considering all three conditions together, the duration of immersion was found to be similar (p &gt; 0.05). No clinical symptoms occurred either during or after immersion. As expected, there was a significant effect of condition on water temperature (F (2,22) = 6293.36, p &lt; 0.001, ω 2 = 1) while other key markers describing exogenous heat dose (ambient temperature and relative humidity) were similar across conditions (all p &gt; 0.05).</p><p>Kinetics of T gi throughout the three conditions are displayed in Figure <ref type="figure">4A</ref>. Prior to immersion, resting T gi values were similar across the three conditions (p = 1). One-way repeated measures ANOVA revealed a significant main effect of CON 36 on T gi across time points (F (1,7) = 7.55; p = 0.007; ω 2 = 0.05); overall, mean T gi slightly decreased in response to CON 36 compared with respective resting values (-0.19°C ± 0.25°C; p = 0.028). There was also a significant effect of HWI 41 (F (1,7) = 145.71; p = 0.001; ω 2 = 0.80) and HWI 40 (F (1,7) = 6.27; p = 0.026; ω 2 = 0.22) on T gi across time points, with both conditions showing a gradual rise in T gi throughout immersion. However, the significant interaction from two-way ANOVA (F (2,21) = 29.09; p &lt; 0.001; ω 2 = 0.37) and subsequent particular comparisons revealed that the increase in T gi was more pronounced during HWI 41 than HWI 40 by the end of immersion (38.76 ± 0.13 vs. 37.96°C ± 0.62°C, p &lt; 0.001, d = 2.88) until the first recovery time point (38.74 ± 0.24 vs. 37.78°C ± 0.61°C; p &lt; 0.001, d = 2.67). Finally, there was a significant effect of thermotherapy on T i&gt;38.5 (F (2,19) = 8.88; p = 0.002; ω 2 = 0.41), with HWI 41 showing a significantly higher T i&gt;38.5 than HWI 40 (p = 0.009).</p><p>No significant main effect of CON 36 was observed on CO across time points (F (5,30) = 0.38; p = 0.856; ω 2 = 0). However, there was a significant effect of HWI 41 (F (1,10) = 17.23; p &lt; 0.001; ω 2 = 0.50) and HWI 40 (F (5,30) = 20.69; p &lt; 0.001; ω 2 = 0.48) on CO across time points, with both conditions showing a gradual rise in CO throughout immersion. However, no interaction was found for CO between HWI 41 and HWI 40 across immersion time points (F (5,65) = 1.73; p = 0.141; ω 2 = 0.02).</p><p>One-way repeated measures ANOVA revealed a significant main effect of CON 36 on SVR across immersion time points (F (6,36) = 11.34; p &lt; 0.001; ω 2 = 0.17); overall, mean SVR increased post-CON 36 compared with resting values (+259 ± 209 dyn.s.cm -5 ; p = 0.017; d = 1.24) while no difference was observed during immersion (all p &gt; 0.05). Bath duration (min) 38.3 ± 6.05 42.0 ± 10.74 47.4 ± 7.40 Ambient T° (°C) 22.4 ± 0.36 22.3 ± 0.20 22.6 ± 0.43 Ambient relative humidity (%) 87.9 ± 1.79 88.9 ± 2.41 89.3 ± 2.06 Endogenous heat dose Zenith T gi (°C) -38.02 ± 0.50* 38.76 ± 0.31* ,# ΔT gi (°C) -0.29 ± 0.24 0.58 ± 0.48* 1.32 ± 0.17* ,# Time spent &gt; 38.5°C (min) 0 ± 0 6.0 ± 11.48 25.5 ± 8.36 * Thermal impulse (°.min) (&gt;38.5°C) 0 ± 0 2.56 ± 6.68 14.9 ± 8.72* ,# Zenith physiological strain index (AU) 0.15 ± 0.42 3.81 ± 1.19* 5.93 ± 0.96* ,# Note: Values are mean ± SD. Abbreviations: CON 36 , warm water immersion (36°C); HWI 40 , hot water immersion (40°C); HWI 41 , hot water immersion (41°C); T°, temperature; T gi , gastrointestinal temperature. *p &lt; 0.05 indicates that HWI 40 and HWI 41 were significantly different from CON 36 . # p &lt; 0.05 indicates that HWI 41 was significantly different from HWI 40 . There was also a significant effect of HWI 41 (F (6,42) = 35.69; p &lt; 0.001; ω 2 = 0.65) and HWI 40 (F (6,36) = 17.02; p &lt; 0.001; ω 2 = 0.55) on SVR across time points, with both conditions showing a gradual decrease in SVR throughout immersion. However, no interaction was found for SVR between HWI 41 and HWI 40 across immersion time points (F (5,65) = 1.98; p = 0.093; ω 2 = 0.03).</p><p>Neither CON 36 (F (5,30) = 0.76; p = 0.59; ω 2 = 0) nor HWI 41 (F (5,35) = 3.52; p = 0.011; ω 2 = 0.16) had a significant effect on SV across immersion time points. However, a significant effect of HWI 40 was observed across immersion time points (F (5,30) = 8.69; p = 0.001; ω 2 = 0.18) with subsequent particular comparisons revealing that SV only increased by the end of immersion (+23.2 ± 13.4 mL.beat -1 , p &lt; 0.001, d = 1.54). with subsequent particular comparisons revealing that [HHb] increased at the end of immersion (+4.2 ± 1.47 μM; p = 0.005, d = 2.18). In addition, the significant interaction from two-way ANOVA (F (5,10) = 2.92; p = 0.003; ω 2 = 0.06) and subsequent particular comparisons revealed that [HHb] was higher during HWI 41 compared with CON 36 (p = 0.026, d = 2.1).</p><p>Neither CON 36 (F (1,7) = 2.64; p = 0.148; ω 2 = 0.02) nor HWI 40 (F (1,7) = 0.06; p = 0.815; ω 2 = 0) had a significant main effect on EDR. Conversely, HWI 41 had a significant main effect on EDR across time points (F (1,7) = 7.10; p = 0.032; ω 2 = 0.24). Overall, mean EDR throughout HWI 41 significantly increased from resting values (19.21 ± 3.85 vs. 15.16 ± 2.63 breath.min -1 , respectively; p = 0.032; d = 1.22).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">| Thermal comfort and thermal sensation</head><p>Kinetics of thermal comfort and thermal sensation throughout the three conditions are displayed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6A</ref>,<ref type="figure">B</ref>.</p><p>No significant main effect of CON 36 was observed on thermal comfort throughout immersion (F (5,30) = 0.77; p = 0.576; ω 2 = 0). Conversely, there was a significant main effect of HWI 41 (F 60% of immersion duration until the end of immersion in both HWI 41 and HWI 40 (all p &lt; 0.05). However, no interaction was found for thermal comfort between HWI 41 and HWI 40 across immersion time points (F (5,70) = 1.92; p = 0.102; ω 2 = 0.02).</p><p>No significant main effect of CON 36 was observed on thermal sensation throughout immersion (F (5,30) = 0.66; p = 0.660; ω 2 = 0). Conversely, there was a significant effect of HWI 41 (F (5,30) = 39.59; p = 0.001; ω 2 = 0.72) and HWI 40 (F (5,30) = 22.14; p = 0.001; ω 2 = 0.50) on thermal sensation across time points, with both conditions showing a gradual rise throughout immersion. More precisely, thermal sensation increased from time points representing 20% of immersion duration until the end of immersion in both HWI 41 and HWI 40 (all p &lt; 0.05). An interaction was found for thermal sensation between HWI 41 and HWI 40 across immersion time points (F (5,65) = 2.50; p = 0.039; ω 2 = 0.05); however, subsequent particular comparisons did not reveal any statistical differences (all p &gt; 0.05).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">| DISCUSSION</head><p>A single HWI 41 session, rather than CON 36 or HWI 40 , provided the necessary level of physiological challenge to mitigate the decline in muscle strength and soreness following exercised-induced muscle damage. By the end of immersion, HWI 41 led to higher gastrointestinal temperature values than HWI 40 . While mean arterial pressure was well maintained throughout immersion, only HWI 41 led to an increase in pre-frontal cortex [HHb]  with a concomitant rise in breathing frequency.</p><p>Our individually tailored EIMD protocol successfully induced quadriceps femoris fatigue, since T peak was significantly reduced in response to sham (i.e., CON 36 ) at post-24 h and post-48 h (Figure <ref type="figure">2A</ref>). In parallel, both RFD 100-200 and PPT of the tired leg were decreased within the same period in response to CON 36 (Figures <ref type="figure">2B</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref>). As both these markers (i.e., RFD 100-200 and PPT) are considered indirect markers of muscle damage, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref> it is reasonable to conclude that our protocol effectively induced muscle damage in all subjects.</p><p>To date, focus has been placed on the early recovery phase (i.e., within hours post-exercise) or the chronic responses to heat (i.e., repeated exposures over several weeks). Taken together, these studies demonstrated positive skeletal muscle adaptations such as increased glycogen resynthesis, improved neuromuscular coupling, and hypertrophy while dampening atrophy-related signaling factors. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> The present results highlighted that heat is also relevant in the late recovery stage (24-48 h) to mitigate the decline in functional variables and muscle soreness following EIMD. However, it is worth noting that the responses to two close exogenous heat doses had divergent effects: the key markers of muscle recovery (i.e., T peak and RFD 100-200 ) returned to baseline values only in HWI 41 and not in both HWI 40 and CON 36 (Figure <ref type="figure">2A</ref>,<ref type="figure">B</ref>). The mechanisms underpinning these findings likely involved the expression of HSP given its crucial role in muscle repair following EIMD. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> Evidence suggests that HSP upregulation is tightly linked to the magnitude of increase in core body temperature. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33</ref> The most striking endogenous difference between the two hot baths was their impact on T gi kinetic, a well-established proxy for core body temperature. A progressive rise in T gi was observed throughout HWI 40 and HWI 41 ; however, it is clear that participants from the HWI 41 condition achieved a significantly higher T gi (~38.8°C) than in HWI 40 (~38.0°C) (Figure <ref type="figure">4A</ref>; Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). In humans, it was suggested that a target core temperature of 38.5°C is required to magnify HSP70 translation/transcription. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34</ref> This dose-response relationship was confirmed in later studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35</ref> Using an exercise-heat model, Gibson and colleagues demonstrated that achieving a core body temperature near-albeit lower than 38.5°C (38.35°C)had no effect on HSP plasma concentration; conversely, only the condition overcoming the aforementioned (temperature) threshold was associated with significant HSP blood accumulation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35</ref> Our results revealed that HWI 41 but not HWI 40 induced the required thermal strain to achieve a sustained (~25 min) core temperature &gt; 38.5°C. In line with this finding, the thermal impulse-a more representative index of total heat strain and strong predictor of HSP mRNA changes <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33</ref> -only increased during HWI 41 (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). Although HSP was not measured in the present study, one may speculate that only HWI 41 induced HSP accumulation, ultimately promoting the faster muscle recovery following HWI 41 . Further studies are essential to clarify whether this temperature threshold applies to local HSP responses, as systemic HSP levels may not accurately reflect the HSP activity within skeletal muscle.</p><p>The beneficial effects reported on muscle function are in agreement with a recent heat-preconditioning study in healthy active males. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> However, one of the main difference with our study is the endogenous heat strain (i.e., core body temperature) achieved by our participants which was lower than in the study of Sabapathy and colleagues (38.8°C vs. 39.4°C, respectively). In our view and as stated by others, the magnitude of hyperthermia that is ethically permissible should not exceed a core body temperature of 39°C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> A hot (and humid) environment will pose a significant thermoregulatory, cardiovascular, and perceptual challenge for an athlete, thereby increasing the likelihood of experiencing heat illnesses, especially in individuals unaccustomed to such physiological challenge. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> Subjective markers of heat strain (thermal comfort/sensation) were similar between HWI 40 and HWI 41 across all time points examined (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6A</ref>,<ref type="figure">B</ref>), despite significant differences in T gi between the two conditions. Consequently, markers based on subjective perception were not adequately sensitive to differentiate between HWI 41 and HWI 40 . By contrast, HWI 41 led to higher HR and T gi values than HWI 40 , thus explaining the higher physiological strain index (PSI) during HWI 41 (5.9) compared with HWI 40 (3.8) by the end of immersion (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). This metric-a more objective marker of endogenous heat stress than thermal sensation/ comfort-demonstrated that the participants from HWI 41 experienced a higher cardiovascular/heat strain than the participants from HWI 40 . PSI is used to classify an individual's response to a given heat challenge, with 0 representing no physiological strain, 10 representing the highest physiological strain and values ≥ 7.5 being considered as at risk of reaching thermal tolerance limit. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36</ref> Participants involved in the study by Sabapathy and colleagues likely achieved a PSI above this "critical" cutoff threshold (i.e., 7.5) since heat exhaustion-like symptoms such as nausea and dizziness were reported. Conversely, in the present study, none of the enrolled participants complained from significant adverse symptoms while in HWI 41 , possibly due to the reduced PSI (&lt;7.5). Taken together, our results indicated that a sustained core body temperature of ~25 min within 38.5°C and 39°C is relevant to improve key markers of muscle recovery in healthy physically active males while limiting the likelihood of experiencing excessive physiological heat strain.</p><p>Heat exposure represents one of the most substantial challenges to integrative cardiovascular function. CO increased in both HWI 41 and HWI 40 by the end of immersion (up to twofold, Figure <ref type="figure">4D</ref>), in line with previous data of passive heating in young, healthy participants. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> It is now well established that the increased CO is primarily driven by an increased HR, as SV is maintained or slightly increased, despite profound reduction in cardiac preload during thermal stress. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> Consistently, in the present study, the rise in HR explained most of the CO response, as SV was either maintained (HWI 41 ) or increased (+36%, HWI 40 ) throughout immersion (Figure <ref type="figure">4F</ref>). In both conditions, the increase in CO offset the large decrease in SVR (Fig- <ref type="figure">ure 4E</ref>) to maintain MAP (Figure <ref type="figure">4C</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> In parallel, NIRS revealed that pre-frontal cortex [HHb] was significantly increased by the end of HWI 41 while no such outcome was observed during HWI 40 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5A</ref>). Mechanistically, this microvascular O 2 delivery-to-utilization mismatch most likely evokes a compromised blood perfusion in the area of NIRS interrogation rather than a diminished arterial O 2 content, since SpO 2 remained constant throughout HWI 41 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5A</ref>). This phenomenon is unlikely due to systemic hypotension since MAP was well maintained throughout HWI 41 (Figure <ref type="figure">4C</ref>). Alternatively, we found that breathing frequency increased during HWI 41 but not during HWI 40 nor CON 36 , thus evoking a hyperventilatory response (i.e., increased minute ventilation) while in HWI 41 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5B</ref>). Hyperventilation-induced (arterial) hypocapnia appears as the primary factor causing cerebrovascular vasoconstriction and decrease in cerebral blood flow with core heating. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38</ref> Interestingly, and as addressed by others, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> there appears to be a core temperature threshold occurring somewhere between +1°C and +1.5°C that triggers heat-induced hyperventilation, hypocapnia, and subsequent decrease in cerebral blood flow. Our data provide further evidence to the existence of this threshold given that T gi rose by ~+ 1.3°C during HWI 41 but only by ~+0.6°C during HWI 40 . Recent data suggest that such an acute cerebrovascular challenge appears safe for the brain parenchyma, at least in young male cohorts. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> However, it is known that central perfusion pressure (i.e., MAP) may be challenged by a decrease in SVR (coupled with sweating) to support heat dissipation. Consequently, when heat stress overlays with an additional cardiovascular challenge, such as standing to exit of the bath, cerebral perfusion may be compromised, which would ultimately increase orthostatic intolerance. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> Therefore, the relevant thermal modality to enhance muscle recovery, that is, HWI 41 , might be at a greater risk than HWI 40 in developing pre-syncopal symptoms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">| Limitations</head><p>A number of limitations have to be considered in this study. In our view, the main one is the lack of continuous intramuscular temperature recording. A simultaneous recording of both core and intramuscular temperature would have offered the opportunity to partly elucidate whether one or both temperatures were determinant for muscle recovery. Finally, it is worth noting that the present study was executed in men. It is suggested that women receiving the same exogenous heat stress as men experience greater rise in core temperature due to their differences in physical characteristics (i.e., smaller body bass and higher fat mass) and sweat rate. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39</ref> In addition, when environmental temperature is higher than skin temperature (as in the present study), women will gain heat faster than men due to their higher surface areato-mass ratio. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40</ref> Taken together, kinetics of core body temperature in response to the two HWI modalities from the present study should not be extrapolated to a cohort of women.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">| CONCLUSION</head><p>The major finding of this study was that a single session of HWI 41 but not HWI 40 provided the required endogenous heat strain to mitigate muscle fatigue and soreness following mild EIMD. The data collected on this population of physically active men suggest that maintaining a core body temperature within the range of 38.5°C-39°C may be advantageous for muscle recovery. Further research is required to elucidate the potential relationships between HSP, core and muscle temperature, and the restoration of muscle function.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">| Perspectives</head><p>From a field perspective, the current study highlights that lower-body HWI appears as a valuable intervention for athletes who require rapid muscle recovery between bouts of strenuous exercise. However, there may be logistical limitations in maintaining water temperature during immersion. Once the subjects were immersed, heat exchange between the water and the body caused the water temperature to decrease below the desired target. This phenomenon occurred despite the use of a dedicated system designed to maintain a constant water temperature. Consequently, frequent monitoring of the water temperature became necessary, and additional hot water from an external source (e.g., tap) was required to sustain the target temperature. Taken together, it is evident that HWI may not be as practical as initially thought when aiming to maintain a specific target temperature within a narrow range, such as 41°C.</p><p>Achieving the core body temperature necessary for optimal muscle recovery may induce a transient disturbance in pre-frontal cortex oxygenation toward the end of immersion, warranting further investigations. Finally, it remains to be determined whether this "optimal" endogenous heat dose applies to women and purposes other than muscle recovery.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNO WLE DGE MENTS</head><p>We are grateful to the participants for their enthusiastic involvement in this study and Jean-Max Bertrand for his technical help with the NIRS device.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>F I G U R E 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Markers of soreness recovery: Individual data points and mean changes from pre-(±SD) for painpressure threshold of the control and tired leg in response to HWI 41 (41°C), HWI 40 (40°C), or warm water immersion (36°C). *p &lt; 0.05 indicates a significant difference from pre-.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>T A B L E 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Exogenous and endogenous heat doses experienced by the athletes. F I G U R E 4 Markers of endogenous heat strain and cardiovascular strain: Mean (±SD) gastrointestinal temperature (A), heart rate (B), mean arterial pressure (MAP, C), cardiac output (D), systemic vascular resistance (E), and stroke volume (F) in response to HWI 41 (41°C), HWI 40 (40°C), or warm water immersion (36°C). *p &lt; 0.05 indicates a significant difference from resting values. # p &lt; 0.05 indicates a significant difference between HWI 41 and CON 36 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>3. 5 |</head><label>5</label><figDesc>SpO2, pre-frontal cortex [HHb], and ECG-derived respiratory frequency Pre-frontal cortex [HHb], SpO 2, and EDR during the three conditions are displayed in Figure 5A,B. Neither CON 36 (F (5,35) = 0.30; p = 0.873; ω 2 = 0), HWI 41 (F (5,40) = 1.12; p = 0.368; ω 2 = 0.01), nor HWI 40 (F (5,30) = 2.47; p = 0.054; ω 2 = 0.10) had a significant effect on SpO 2 across immersion time points. Neither CON 36 (F (5,41) = 0.47; p = 0.794; ω 2 = 0) nor HWI 40 (F (5,29) = 0.57; p = 0.723; ω 2 = 0) had a significant effect on [HHb] across immersion time points. However, a significant effect of HWI 41 was observed across immersion time points (F (5,35) = 3.46; p = 0.012; ω 2 = 0.23)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc>(5,40) = 44.58; p = 0.001; ω 2 = 0.68) and HWI 40 (F (5,30) = 19.49; p = 0.001; ω 2 = 0.50) on thermal comfort across time points, with both conditions showing a gradual rise throughout immersion. More precisely, thermal comfort increased from time points representing F I G U R E 5 Mean (±SD) of pre-frontal deoxyhemoglobin ([HHb], A) and peripheral oxygen saturation (SpO 2 , A). Individual data points and mean changes from resting (±SD) for ECG-derived respiratory frequency (EDR, B) during HWI 41 (41°C), HWI 40 (40°C), or warm water immersion (CON 36 ). Note that unlike other measured hemodynamic parameters, post-immersion [HHb] kinetics are note displayed since the NIRS probe had to be removed due to significant discomfort in most participants. Panel A: *p &lt; 0.05 indicates a significant difference from resting. # p &lt; 0.05 indicates a significant difference between HWI 41 and CON 36 . Panel B: *p &lt; 0.05 indicates a significant difference from resting values.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>F I G U R E 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Markers of subjective perception: Mean (±SD) thermal comfort (A) and thermal sensation (B) in response to HWI 41 (41°C), HWI 40 (40°C), or warm water immersion (CON 36 ). *p &lt; 0.05 indicates a significant difference from resting values.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="3,48.43,452.14,498.42,262.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="8,45.64,46.70,331.65,491.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>16000838, 2024, 1, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/sms.14503 by &lt;Shibboleth&gt; member@tudublin.ie, Wiley Online Library on [10/08/2024]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			
			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>No specific grant was allocated for the execution of the current research study</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT</head><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">| Hemodynamic parameters</head><p>Kinetics of HR, MAP, CO, SVR, and SV throughout the three conditions are displayed in Figure <ref type="figure">4B-F</ref>.</p><p>No significant main effect of CON 36 was observed on HR across time points (F (6,36) = 2.05; p = 0.085; ω 2 = 0.01). However, there was a significant effect of HWI 41 (F (5,35)  However, the significant interaction from two-way ANOVA (F (5,65) = 5.97; p &lt; 0.001; ω 2 = 0.08) and subsequent particular comparisons revealed that increase in HR was more pronounced during HWI 41 than HWI 40 by the end of immersion (127.8 ± 13.43 vs. 102.1°C ± 17.50°C, p = 0.012, d = 2.19).</p><p>Neither CON 36 (F (6,36) = 2.22; p = 0.063; ω 2 = 0.04) nor HWI 40 (F (6,36) = 0.42; p = 0.864; ω 2 = 0) had a significant effect on MAP across immersion time points. However, a significant effect of HWI 41 was observed across immersion time points (F (6,42) = 3.92; p = 0.003; ω 2 = 0.05) with subsequent particular comparisons revealing that MAP only decreased at the time point representing 40% of immersion duration (-7.6 ± 6.44 mmHg, p = 0.021, d = 0.76).</p><p>F I G U R E 2 Markers of muscle recovery: Individual data points and mean changes from pre-(±SD) for torque peak (A), late-phase rate of force development (RDF 100-200 , B) in response to HWI 41 (41°C), HWI 40 (40°C), or warm water immersion (36°C). In panel A, note that the "acute" phase refers to the acute fatigue (i.e., drop in T peak ) immediately following EIMD. *p &lt; 0.05 indicates a significant difference from pre-.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT</head><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exerciseinduced muscle damage: what is it, what causes it and what are the nutritional solutions?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Owens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Twist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Cobley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Howatson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Close</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Sport Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Owens DJ, Twist C, Cobley JN, Howatson G, Close GL. Exercise- induced muscle damage: what is it, what causes it and what are the nutritional solutions? Eur J Sport Sci. 2019;19(1):71-85.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Eccentric exercise: physiological characteristics and acute responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pearson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mcguigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sports Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="663" to="675" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Douglas J, Pearson S, Ross A, McGuigan M. Eccentric exercise: physiological characteristics and acute responses. Sports Med. 2017;47(4):663-675.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The importance of muscular strength in athletic performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Suchomel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nimphius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sports Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1419" to="1449" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Suchomel TJ, Nimphius S, Stone MH. The importance of mus- cular strength in athletic performance. Sports Med. 2016;46(10): 1419-1449.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Athlete, coach and practitioner knowledge and perceptions of post-exercise cold-water immersion for recovery: a qualitative and quantitative exploration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Allan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Akin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sinclair</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sport Sci Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="699" to="713" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Allan R, Akin B, Sinclair J, et al. Athlete, coach and practitioner knowledge and perceptions of post-exercise cold-water immer- sion for recovery: a qualitative and quantitative exploration. Sport Sci Health. 2022;18(3):699-713.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effects of cold water immersion and active recovery on inflammation and cell stress responses in human skeletal muscle after resistance exercise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Peake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Figueiredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">595</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="695" to="711" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Peake JM, Roberts LA, Figueiredo VC, et al. The effects of cold water immersion and active recovery on inflammation and cell stress responses in human skeletal muscle after resistance exer- cise. J Physiol. 2017;595(3):695-711.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Postexercise cold water immersion benefits are not greater than the placebo effect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Broatch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bishop</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Sci Sports Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2139" to="2147" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Broatch JR, Petersen A, Bishop DJ. Postexercise cold water im- mersion benefits are not greater than the placebo effect. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2014;46(11):2139-2147.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional impact of post-exercise cooling and heating on recovery and training adaptations: application to resistance, endurance, and Sprint exercise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chaillou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Treigyte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mosely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brazaitis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Venckunas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sports Med Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">37</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chaillou T, Treigyte V, Mosely S, Brazaitis M, Venckunas T, Cheng AJ. Functional impact of post-exercise cooling and heating on recovery and training adaptations: application to resistance, endurance, and Sprint exercise. Sports Med Open. 2022;8(1):37.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Post-exercise recovery of contractile function and endurance in humans and mice is accelerated by heating and slowed by cooling skeletal muscle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Willis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zinner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">595</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7413" to="7426" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cheng AJ, Willis SJ, Zinner C, et al. Post-exercise recovery of contractile function and endurance in humans and mice is ac- celerated by heating and slowed by cooling skeletal muscle. J Physiol. 2017;595(24):7413-7426.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Warm underwater water-jet massage improves recovery from intense physical exercise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Viitasalo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Niemelä</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kaappola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europ J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Viitasalo J, Niemelä K, Kaappola R, et al. Warm underwater water-jet massage improves recovery from intense physical ex- ercise. Europ J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol. 1995;71(5):431-438.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Short term effects of various water immersions on recovery from exhaustive intermittent exercise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pournot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bieuzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Duffield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P-M</forename><surname>Lepretre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cozzolino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hausswirth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1287" to="1295" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pournot H, Bieuzen F, Duffield R, Lepretre P-M, Cozzolino C, Hausswirth C. Short term effects of various water immersions on recovery from exhaustive intermittent exercise. Eur J Appl Physiol. 2011;111(7):1287-1295.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of hydrotherapy on the signs and symptoms of delayed onset muscle soreness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vaile</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Halson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Gill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="447" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vaile J, Halson S, Gill N, Dawson B. Effect of hydrotherapy on the signs and symptoms of delayed onset muscle soreness. Eur J Appl Physiol. 2008;102(4):447-455.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximal eccentric exercise induces a rapid accumulation of small heat shock proteins on myofibrils and a delayed HSP70 response in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Paulsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vissing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kalhovde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">293</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="844" to="R853" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Paulsen G, Vissing K, Kalhovde JM, et al. Maximal eccentric exercise induces a rapid accumulation of small heat shock pro- teins on myofibrils and a delayed HSP70 response in humans. Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol. 2007;293(2):R844-R853.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The heat shock connection: skeletal muscle hypertrophy and atrophy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fennel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Amorim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Deyhle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hafen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mermier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">323</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="R148" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fennel ZJ, Amorim FT, Deyhle MR, Hafen PS, Mermier CM. The heat shock connection: skeletal muscle hypertrophy and atrophy. Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol. 2022;323(1):R1 33-R148.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Daily heat treatment maintains mitochondrial function and attenuates atrophy in human skeletal muscle subjected to immobilization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hafen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Abbott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bowden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lopiano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hancock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hyldahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hafen PS, Abbott K, Bowden J, Lopiano R, Hancock CR, Hyldahl RD. Daily heat treatment maintains mitochondrial function and attenuates atrophy in human skeletal muscle sub- jected to immobilization. J Appl Physiol. 2019;127(1):47-57.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Skeletal muscle adaptations to heat therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Monroe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gavin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Roseguini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1635" to="1642" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kim K, Monroe JC, Gavin TP, Roseguini BT. Skeletal muscle adaptations to heat therapy. J Appl Physiol. 2020;128(6):1635-1642.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hot-water immersion does not increase postprandial muscle protein synthesis rates during recovery from resistance-type exercise in healthy, Young Males</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jsj</forename><surname>Smeets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Senden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1012" to="1022" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fuchs CJ, Smeets JSJ, Senden JM, et al. Hot-water immersion does not increase postprandial muscle protein synthesis rates during recovery from resistance-type exercise in healthy, Young Males. J Appl Physiol. 2020;128(4):1012-1022.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IOC consensus Statement on recommendations and regulations for sport events in the heat</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Racinais</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hosokawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Akama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Sports Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Racinais S, Hosokawa Y, Akama T, et al. IOC consensus Statement on recommendations and regulations for sport events in the heat. Br J Sports Med. 2023;57(1):8-25.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of heat preconditioning on recovery following exercise-induced muscle damage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sabapathy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Al</forename><surname>Hussein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Res Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="162" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sabapathy M, Tan F, Al Hussein S, et al. Effect of heat pre- conditioning on recovery following exercise-induced muscle damage. Curr Res Physiol. 2021;4:155-162.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classic and exertional heatstroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bouchama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Abuyassin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lehe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Dis Primers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bouchama A, Abuyassin B, Lehe C, et al. Classic and exertional heatstroke. Nat Rev Dis Primers. 2022;8(1):8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of responses of men to immersion in circulating water at 40.0 and 41.5 degrees C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Allison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Reger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aviat Space Environ Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="845" to="850" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Allison TG, Reger WE. Comparison of responses of men to im- mersion in circulating water at 40.0 and 41.5 degrees C. Aviat Space Environ Med. 1998;69(9):845-850.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Negligible influence of moderate to severe hyperthermia on blood-brain barrier permeability and neuronal parenchymal integrity in healthy men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shepley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Ainslie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hoiland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="792" to="800" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Shepley BR, Ainslie PN, Hoiland RL, et al. Negligible influence of moderate to severe hyperthermia on blood-brain barrier permeability and neuronal parenchymal integrity in healthy men. J Appl Physiol. 2021;130(3):792-800.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is all heat equal? Implications for the stimulus for adaptation In the brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gibbons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">598</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2051" to="2052" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gibbons TD, Thomas KN, Wilson LC. Is all heat equal? Implications for the stimulus for adaptation In the brain. J Physiol. 2020;598(11):2051-2052.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms of orthostatic intolerance during heat stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schlader</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Crandall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Auton Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">196</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schlader ZJ, Wilson TE, Crandall CG. Mechanisms of or- thostatic intolerance during heat stress. Auton Neurosci. 2016;196:37-46.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exertional heat stroke: an evidence based approach to clinical assessment and management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Degroot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O'</forename><surname>Connor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1172" to="1183" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">DeGroot DW, O&apos;Connor FG, Roberts WO. Exertional heat stroke: an evidence based approach to clinical assessment and management. Exp Physiol. 2022;107(10):1172-1183.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of two telemetric intestinal temperature devices with rectal temperature during exercise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bogerd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Velt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Annaheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ccwg</forename><surname>Bongers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tmh</forename><surname>Eijsvogels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ham</forename><surname>Daanen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiol Meas</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="03N" to="T4" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bogerd CP, Velt KB, Annaheim S, Bongers CCWG, Eijsvogels TMH, Daanen HAM. Comparison of two telemetric intestinal temperature devices with rectal temperature during exercise. Physiol Meas. 2018;39(3):03NT01.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Serum S-100beta response to exercise-heat strain before and after acclimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Cheuvront</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Chinevere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ely</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Sci Sports Exerc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1477" to="1482" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cheuvront SN, Chinevere TD, Ely BR, et al. Serum S-100beta response to exercise-heat strain before and after acclimation. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2008;40(8):1477-1482.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A physiological strain index to evaluate heat stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Moran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Pandolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">275</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="R134" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Moran DS, Shitzer A, Pandolf KB. A physiological strain index to evaluate heat stress. Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol. 1998;275(1):R129-R134.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leucocytes, cytokines and satellite cells: what role do they play in muscle damage and regeneration following eccentric exercise?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Paulsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mikkelsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Raastad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Peake</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exerc Immunol Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Paulsen G, Mikkelsen UR, Raastad T, Peake JM. Leucocytes, cytokines and satellite cells: what role do they play in muscle damage and regeneration following eccentric exercise? Exerc Immunol Rev. 2012;18:42-97.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rate of force development as a measure of muscle damage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Peñailillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Blazevich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Numazawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nosaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scand J Med Sci Sports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="427" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Peñailillo L, Blazevich A, Numazawa H, Nosaka K. Rate of force development as a measure of muscle damage. Scand J Med Sci Sports. 2015;25(3):417-427.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calculation of mean arterial pressure during exercise as a function of heart rate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Epstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Keren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Laor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sherez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl Human Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="295" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Moran D, Epstein Y, Keren G, Laor A, Sherez J, Shapiro Y. Calculation of mean arterial pressure during exercise as a func- tion of heart rate. Appl Human Sci. 1995;14(6):293-295.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Breathing rate estimation from the electrocardiogram and Photoplethysmogram: a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Charlton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Birrenkott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bonnici</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Rev Biomed Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Charlton PH, Birrenkott DA, Bonnici T, et al. Breathing rate es- timation from the electrocardiogram and Photoplethysmogram: a review. IEEE Rev Biomed Eng. 2018;11:2-20.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The pain threshold of high-threshold mechanosensitive receptors subsequent to maximal eccentric exercise is a potential marker in the prediction of DOMS associated impairment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fleckenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>König</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Banzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">185463</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fleckenstein J, Simon P, König M, Vogt L, Banzer W. The pain threshold of high-threshold mechanosensitive receptors sub- sequent to maximal eccentric exercise is a potential marker in the prediction of DOMS associated impairment. PLoS One. 2017;12(10):e0185463.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hsp72 and Hsp90α mRNA transcription is characterised by large, sustained changes in Core temperature during heat acclimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tuttle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Watt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Maxwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Stress Chaperones</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1021" to="1035" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gibson OR, Tuttle JA, Watt PW, Maxwell NS, Taylor L. Hsp72 and Hsp90α mRNA transcription is characterised by large, sus- tained changes in Core temperature during heat acclimation. Cell Stress Chaperones. 2016;21(6):1021-1035.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of the rate of heat storage on serum heat shock protein 72 in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Amorim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Robergs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Moseley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="965" to="972" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Amorim FT, Yamada PM, Robergs RA, Schneider SM, Moseley PL. The effect of the rate of heat storage on serum heat shock protein 72 in humans. Eur J Appl Physiol. 2008;104(6):965-972.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracellular Hsp72 concentration relates to a minimum endogenous criteria during acute exercise-heat exposure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Parfitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Watt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Maxwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Stress Chaperones</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="400" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gibson OR, Dennis A, Parfitt T, Taylor L, Watt PW, Maxwell NS. Extracellular Hsp72 concentration relates to a minimum endogenous criteria during acute exercise-heat exposure. Cell Stress Chaperones. 2014;19(3):389-400.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A real-time heat strain risk classifier using heart rate and skin temperature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Buller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Latzka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yokota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tharion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Moran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiol Meas</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="N85" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Buller MJ, Latzka WA, Yokota M, Tharion WJ, Moran DS. A real-time heat strain risk classifier using heart rate and skin temperature. Physiol Meas. 2008;29(12):N79-N85.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human cardiovascular responses to passive heat stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Crandall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Compr Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Crandall CG, Wilson TE. Human cardiovascular responses to passive heat stress. Compr Physiol. 2015;5(1):17-43.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regional changes in brain blood flow during severe passive hyperthermia: effects of PaCO 2 and extracranial blood flow</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="653" to="659" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bain AR, Smith KJ, Lewis NC, et al. Regional changes in brain blood flow during severe passive hyperthermia: effects of PaCO 2 and extracranial blood flow. J Appl Physiol. 2013;115(5):653-659.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling of gender differences in thermoregulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Iyoho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Macfadden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mil Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">182</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">suppl_1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="303" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Iyoho AE, Ng LJ, MacFadden L. Modeling of gender dif- ferences in thermoregulation. Mil Med. 2017;182 (suppl_1): 295-303.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct status="extracted"  xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sex differences in human thermoregulation: relevance for 2020 and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yanovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ketko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Charkoudian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiology (Bethesda)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="184" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Yanovich R, Ketko I, Charkoudian N. Sex differences in human thermoregulation: relevance for 2020 and beyond. Physiology (Bethesda). 2020;35(3):177-184.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
